<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Everyday Utilitarian</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com" />
<updated>2014-06-04T16:16:02-04:00</updated>
<id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/</id>
<author>
  <name></name>
  <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/</uri>
  <email></email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Re-Analysis of ACE's Leaflet Study]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/a-re-analysis-of-ace-leaflet-study/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/a-re-analysis-of-ace-leaflet-study</id>
  <published>2014-06-04T05:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-06-04T05:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Now that I’ve been doing some research blogging, it’s time to continue the trend with something big.  Maybe you’ve seen &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalcharityevaluators.org/research/interventions/leafleting/leafleting-outreach-study-fall-2013/leafleting-outreach-study-analysis-fall-2013/&quot;&gt;ACE’s leafleting study analysis&lt;/a&gt; and was like “woah, that’s long, no way I’m going to read all that”.  Instead, my reaction was “that’s long, but is there any way I can make it longer?”  So I did.  14.5 + today hours later, I emerge with this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalcharityevaluators.org/&quot;&gt;Animal Charity Evaluators&lt;/a&gt; (ACE) is a non-profit with the goal of using research to find ways to help more save nonhuman animals with the same amount of resources.  Given that the pro-nonhuman movement is quite small, any increase in our “bang for our buck” is quite important, and I welcome this research and aim to contribue to it myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.veganoutreach.org/&quot;&gt;Vegan Outreach&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thehumaneleague.com&quot;&gt;The Humane League&lt;/a&gt; are two pro-nonhuman non-profits that aim to do direct advocacy on behalf of non-human animals.  One thing they do is deliver leaflets to people aiming to convince people about the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.veganoutreach.org/whyvegan/animals.html&quot;&gt;horrors of factory farming&lt;/a&gt; and convince them to &lt;a href=&quot;everydayutilitarian.com/essays/why-eat-less-meat&quot;&gt;eat less meat&lt;/a&gt;.  ACE claims that this is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalcharityevaluators.org/research/interventions/leafleting/&quot;&gt;one of the most cost-effective ways to help non-human animals&lt;/a&gt;, but wants to put this to the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the latter half of 2013, Joey Savoie and Xio Kikauka, in cooperation with Animal Charity Evaluators, implemented a study of the impact of two Vegan Outreach leaflets on diet change.  In March 2014, ACE &lt;a href=&quot;ttp://www.animalcharityevaluators.org/research/interventions/leafleting/leafleting-outreach-study-fall-2013/leafleting-outreach-study-analysis-fall-2013/&quot;&gt;released their analysis&lt;/a&gt; in cooperation with Statisticians Without Borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was personally somewhat skeptical of the analysis and though there was a decent amount of information still being left on the table.  I wanted to take advantage of the publicly provided dataset to do my own independent analysis to see what I could personally learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did my best to check for errors, but it’s quite possible errors in my analysis may still remain. &lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This blog post in one sentence:&lt;/strong&gt; ACE’s claims are broadly correct, though perhaps overstated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not feel like the study provides any positive evidence for vegetarian conversion as a whole, so ACE’s claim that “[w]e found support for claims that distributing leaflets from Vegan Outreach (or similar leaflets published by other groups) causes a small percentage of respondents to go vegetarian” is overstated.  I also think there is more nuance affecting some of their conclusions than ACE’s analysis admits, though to ACE’s credit, they are pretty self-skeptical about their own results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think ACE should be appluaded for having a good degree of self-skepticism, a high degree of transparency, and doing great with going through pre-registration and other checks to make sure they wouldn’t be fooling themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, one’s attitude toward these results depends really on how skeptical and negative one wants to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reasons-for-positivity-toward-leafleting&quot;&gt;Reasons for positivity toward leafleting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rates of people eliminating both red meat and poultry after receiving the treatment leaflet were quite high at 2.5% (4/161).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The connection between the treatment leaflet and elimination of red meat and poultry was statistically significant.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The sample size of this study was underpowered enough that it could have missed an effect under 6% with &amp;gt;20% chance, and almost certainly would miss an effect at 1% or below.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reasons-for-negativity-toward-leafleting&quot;&gt;Reasons for negativity toward leafleting&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rates of people becoming entirely vegetarian were quite low at 0.56% (1/178) and this was not statistically significant (even before Bonferroni corrections).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Treatment leaflets appear to have no effect on fish, eggs, or dairy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The connection between the treatment leaflet and elimination of red meat and poultry was no longer statistically significant after Bonferroni corrections.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The change in eliminating red meat and poultry derived from the food frequency questionnaires did not correspond with changes from people stating that they “went pescatarian”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are methodological problems with both food frequency questionnaires and with asking people about their diet change in terms of “vegetarian” and “pescetarian”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-the-dataset&quot;&gt;Setting up the Dataset&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start, I went to the survey dataset, downloaded a copy as a csv, removed the first row, and imported the file into R.  The provided survey questions and guide to the data were very useful in interpreting the dataset, and I thank ACE for making it so easy to do this re-analysis.  It reflects really well on their value for transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/peterhurford/personal/blob/gh-pages/tilde/files/leaflets.R&quot;&gt;R script for doing the re-analysis is here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-should-the-independent-variable-be&quot;&gt;What should the independent variable be?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I set up the dataset, I looked into how we should represent the independent variable – the amount of change in diet caused by the survey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;meat-elimination&quot;&gt;Meat Elimination&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Question 1 asked about the amount of foods people eat now and Question 3 asks about the amount of foods people ate three months ago.  I summed up the total ranks across red meat, poultry, and fish/seafood for both present and three months ago.  I then compared these totals and looked for people who had no meat consumption at present but did consume meat three months ago (meat eliminator), people who consumed meat both in present and three months ago (no change), and people who consumed meat at present but did not consume meat three months ago (meat adders).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Meat Eliminator&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;No Change&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Meat Adder&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;N&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;4 (0.8%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;532 (99%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1 (0.2%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;537&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that while 0.8% new vegetarians might look low, we still have not yet compared that population to the leaflet-receiving population, and thus still cannot make any conclusions about how many people given they receive a leaflet, go vegetarian – that percentage could still be much higher (or lower).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;meat-reduction&quot;&gt;Meat Reduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how much I trust the Food Frequency Questionnaires to provide accurate and precise measures of people’s diets, so I’m a bit uncomfortable trying to tease meat reduction out of the dataset (as is the ACE analysis).  However, there is also a problem that outright elimination happens too infrequently (only 0.8% of the data set), so we might want a variable that is more easily changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I compared the past and current consumption of meat and this time assigned categories for Reduced, Stayed the Same, and Increased, looking at relative changes rather than outright elimination.  I do not think this is a variable ACE looked at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Meat Reducer&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;No Change&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Meat Increaser&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;N&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;174 (32.4%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;243 (45.3%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;120 (22.3%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;537&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;red-meat-elimination&quot;&gt;Red Meat Elimination&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ACE spent a lot of their analysis looking at how consumption of individual foods changed as a way to measure meat reduction.  I was particularly interested at people’s elimination of red meat, as this is a type of meat frequently eliminated first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Red Meat Eliminator&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;No Change&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Red Meat Adder&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;N&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;13 (2.3%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;539 (96.4%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;7 (1.3%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;559&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;poultry-elimination&quot;&gt;Poultry Elimination&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As ACE found positive results for poultry as well, I looked at that too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Poultry Eliminator&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;No Change&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Poultry Adder&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;N&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;8 (1.4%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;547 (98%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;3 (0.6%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;558&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the people even eliminated both.  Six people were found to eliminate both poultry and red meat, with nine people eliminating just one (seven for just red meat, two for just poultry).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;change-in-declared-vegetarianism-and-veganism&quot;&gt;Change in Declared Vegetarianism and Veganism&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to food frequency questionnaires, the survey also asked people if they identified as vegetarian or vegan at present and if they identified as vegetarian or vegan three months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Omnivore (3mo ago)&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Vegetarian (3mo ago)&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Vegan (3mo ago)&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Omnivore (present)&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Vegetarian (present)&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Vegan (present)&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;578&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;32&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;570&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Vegan to Omnivore&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Vegetarian to Omnivore&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Vegan to Vegetarian&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;No Change&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Vegetarian to Vegan&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Omnivore to Vegetarian&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Omnivore to Vegan&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;572&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;change-in-declared-pescetarianism-and-intent-to-reduce-meat&quot;&gt;Change in Declared Pescetarianism and Intent to Reduce Meat&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we were looking at whether people were dropping red meat and poultry, I was also curious if this would match up with people personally identifying as pescatarians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Reducer (3mo ago)&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Pescatarian (3mo ago)&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Reducer (present)&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Pescatarian (present)&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;35&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;33&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Pescatarian to Omnivore&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Reducer to Omnivore&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Pescatarian to Reducer&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;No Change&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Reducer to Pescatarian&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Omnivore to Reducer&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Omnivore to Pescatarian&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;527&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges-to-these-variables&quot;&gt;Challenges to These Variables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why look at eight different independent variables?  One reason was that we were interested in both partial meat elimination and full meat elimination.  But another reason is that it’s really hard to figure out who exactly is vegetarian…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;first-problem-vegetarians-and-vegans-eat-meat&quot;&gt;First Problem: Vegetarians and Vegans Eat Meat&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weird, I know.  But it seems like people report themselves as “vegetarian” or “vegan” without knowing what it really means.  The good news is that vegetarians and vegans do eat less meat.  But the weird thing is that they still do eat meat.  Therefore, we may have someone who claim they became vegan, but all that might mean in reality is that they merely reduced their meat consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;caption&gt;Mean “Ranks” in Meat Eating by Diet Status (Reverse coded so higher = more meat eating)&lt;/caption&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Red Meat&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;All Meat&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;All Animal Products&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Omnivore&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;2.97 / 7&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;8.2 / 21&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;14.30 / 35&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Vegetarian&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;0.97 / 7&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;2.6 / 21&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;8.51 / 35&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Vegan&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;0.43 / 7&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1.7 / 21&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;3.69 / 35&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;second-problem-food-frequency-questionnaires-seem-troublesome&quot;&gt;Second Problem: Food Frequency Questionnaires Seem Troublesome&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick!  How many servings of cheese did you eat three months ago?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t know the answer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…Can you ballpark it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me neither.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But yet this is the alternative method of figuring out whether people go vegetarian or reduce meat consumption – compare their actual diets from three months ago to now.  These food frequency questionnaires are standard to the nutrition science industry, so they might be the be best we’ve got.  But I’m skeptical of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-should-the-relevant-treatment-and-control-groups-be&quot;&gt;What should the relevant treatment and control groups be?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re looking to five different independent variables to track changes in diet.  But we’re really interested in the impact of leafleting.  The study was designed well – there was a control leaflet and two different treatment leaflets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;caption&gt;Leaflets Recognized by Follow-up Survey Respondents&lt;/caption&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;EIYLM (treatment)&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;CC (treatment)&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;CBTC (control)&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Fictional Flyer&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;No Leaflet&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;95&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;125&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;44&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;428&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EIYLM = Even if You Like Meat, CC = Compassion Over Cruelty, CBTC = Cruelty Behind the Cuteness.  Note: The same respondent may be in multiple categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problems-with-the-control-group&quot;&gt;Problems with the Control Group&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like it might be easy to sort people into a treatment group and a control group.  However, because people received multiple leaflets, a lot of people who received the control leaflet also received the treatment leaflet, which means that they’re in the treatment group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;caption&gt;Leaflets Recognized by Follow-up Survey Respondents&lt;/caption&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Treatment Leaflet Group&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Control Leaflet Group&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;No Leaflet&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;178&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;428&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes a control group that is much smaller than we need to use.  The ACE analysis decides to use the No Leaflet group as a secondary control group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;problems-with-leaflet-recall&quot;&gt;Problems with Leaflet Recall&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fictional flyer refers to participants erroneously identifying receiving a flyer that was never handed out – at least five people were duped by this, so there’s probably other errors with people remembering which leaflet they actually received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, ACE mentions that more than sixty people also mention receiving a treatment leaflet that was not actually handed out at their location.  This means some people may have sorted themselves into the wrong treatment or control group, messing with our results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-changes-reportedly-occurred-as-a-result-of-the-leafleting&quot;&gt;What changes reportedly occurred as a result of the leafleting?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now that we have eight potential independent variables and three groups to look at, how did things actually turn out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Treatment Flyer&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Control Flyer&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;No Flyer&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Meat Elimination&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Elim: 1/158 (0.6%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 156/158 (98.7%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Add: 1/158 (0.6%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Elim: 0/15 (0%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 15/15 (100%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Add: 0/15 (0%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Elim: 3/364 (0.8%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 361/364 (99.2%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Add: 0/364 (0%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Meat Reduction&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Dec: 62/158 (39.2%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 67/158 (42.4%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Inc: 29/158 (18.4%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Dec: 3/15 (20%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 8/15 (53.3%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Inc: 4/15 (26.7%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Dec: 109/364 (29.9%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 168/364 (46.2%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Inc: 87/364 (23.9%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Red Meat Elimination&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Elim: 7/162 (4.3%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 155/162 (95.7%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Add: 0/162 (0%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Elim: 0/16 (0%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 16/16 (100%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Add: 0/16 (0%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Elim: 7/381 (1.8%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 368/381 (96.6%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Add: 6/381 (1.6%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Poultry Elimination&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Elim: 5/165 (3%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 160/165 (97%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Add: 0/165 (0%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Elim: 0/15 (0%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 15/15 (100%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Add: 0/15 (0%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;
			Elim: 3/378 (0.8%)&lt;br /&gt;
			None: 372/378 (98.4%)&lt;br /&gt;
			Add: 3/378 (0.8%)
		&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Net Vegetarians and Vegans Added&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;3/178 (1.7%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;0/17 (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;5/428 (1.2%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Net Pescetarians Added&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;4/178 (2.5%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1/17 (5.9%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;0/428 (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Net Meat Reducers Added&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;4/178 (2.5%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;0/17 (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;5/428 (1.2%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are these differences statistically significant?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just looking at the table, it appears that a Vegan Outreach flyer does produce more meat reduction, red meat elimination, and net vegetarians/vegans added, relative to the control and no flyer groups, though it also seems to produce less meat elimination than the control / no flyer groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the differences across the groups could just be due to chance.  To be sure, let’s compare across the groups with T-tests.  We’ll compare the population of those who received the treatment flyer to the population receiving the control flyer and then the wider population of everyone sampled who did not receive the treatment flyer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Treatment vs. Control&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Treatment vs. Non-treatment&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Meat Elimination&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = 0.78, p = NS&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = 0.00, p = NS&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Overall Meat Reduction&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = -1.44, p = NS&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = -2.21, p = 0.03&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Red Meat Elimination&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = -2.69, p = 0.01&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = -2.48, p = 0.01&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Poultry Elimination&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = -2.26, p = 0.02&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = -2.05, p = 0.04&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Net Vegetarians / Vegans Added&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = -1.00, p = 0.32&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = -0.30, p = 0.76&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Net Pescatarians Added&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = 0.59, p = 0.56&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = -0.99, p = 0.33&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Net Meat Reducers Added&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = -1.15, p = 0.25&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;t = -0.51, p = 0.61&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this, the statistically significant effect of treatment flyers is muddled.  They do have statistically significant effects on meat reduction, red meat elimination, and poultry elimination, but there is no corresponding statistically significant effect with declared pescatarianism or declared intent to reduce meat.  And no other variables are statistically significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, it’s also worth noting that ACE did not do any sort of corrections for doing multiple statistical tests.  When we do a Bonferroni correction here, having done fourteen separate analyses, we reduce our threshold for statistical significance from p = 0.05 to p = 0.05/14, or 0.003, which no tests met.  Even a less stringent test, such as starting from p = 0.1 before Bonferroni corrections is not met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-much-can-flyers-be-attributed-to-these-changes&quot;&gt;How much can flyers be attributed to these changes?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way we can look a little bit closer is with variables that (a) self-report how much of the leaflet was actually read, (b) self-report how influential the leaflet was, and (c) self-report the reason for changing diets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-much-of-each-leaflet-was-read&quot;&gt;How much of each leaflet was read?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Did not read&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Glanced&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Read some&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Read all&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;EIYLM (treat)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;9 (9%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;26 (27%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;34 (36%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;26 (27%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;CC (treat)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;12 (10%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;33 (27%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;44 (35%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;35 (28%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;CBTC (control)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;6 (14%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;15 (35%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;16 (37%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;6 (14%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Fictional flyer&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;0 (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;4 (80%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1 (20%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;0 (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;No flyer&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;155 (82%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;17 (9%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;7 (4%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;9 (5%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting that reading patterns for the treatment leaflets are statistically identical (p = 0.11), but statistically distinct from the control flyer (p = 0.05).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…Also of problematic interest is how many people claimed never to receive a flyer, yet claimed to have read a flyer anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-influential-were-the-leaflets&quot;&gt;How influential were the leaflets?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Leaflet caused diet change&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Thinking differently about farming&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Thinking differently about pets&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;Possible effect&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;th&gt;No effect&lt;/th&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;EIYLM (treat)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;7 (7%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;18 (19%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;6 (6%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;26 (28%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;37 (39%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;CC (treat)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;11 (9%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;28 (23%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;2 (2%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;29 (24%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;53 (43%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;CBTC (control)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;2  (5%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;6 (1%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;4 (10%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;13 (31%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;17 (40%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Fictional flyer&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;0 (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1 (25%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;0 (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;2 (50%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1 (25%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;No flyer&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;0 (0%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;8 (4%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;10 (5%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;39 (22%)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;124 (69%)&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;6 people who received the treatment flyer self-reported becoming a vegetarian or vegan.  Of these…&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;5 out of the 6 reported reading all of the leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1 out of the 6 report having their diet changed by the leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2 out of the 6 report the leaflet having zero impact on their diet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2 out of the 6 report changing their diet for animal cruelty or ethical reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can also use this to dig a little bit deeper at red meat reduction, one of the independent variables credited by ACE as being affected by the leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;7 people who received the treatment flyer self-reported eliminating red meat.  Of these…&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;2 out of the 7 reported reading all of the leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4 out of the 7 report having their diet changed by the leaflet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;1 out of the 7 report the leaflet having zero impact on their diet.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4 out of the 7 report changing their diet for animal cruelty or ethical reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is good as a check of our results above – we have found that some of the people who appear converted by the leaflet also agree that they were converted.  Moreover, I was concerned that people switching to eliminate red meat would be doing so for health reasons alone, and this does not appear to be the case, nearest as we can tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though take this all with a grain of salt – if you have middling confidence in people’s ability to self-report their diet, like I do, you probably should also have middling confidence in people’s ability to understand how much the leaflet affected them.  I do think you can justify slightly higher confidence in these numbers, as it’s more salient and potentially easier to recall than precise numbers about your diet, but people are still generally bad at retrospecting on causal influences on their life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-are-preliminary-lower-and-upper-bounds-for-flyer-conversion-rates&quot;&gt;What are preliminary lower and upper bounds for flyer conversion rates?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lower Bound&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;178 treatment flyers were given out, and it appears quite plausible (as clear as can be determined by the survey, given that you trust self-reported data) that precisely one person was lead to become a (genuine) vegetarian specifically based on having received the treatment flyer.  One could consider this as establishing a preliminary lower bound on conversion rates at 0.56%, though I would be careful not to generalize from solely one person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upper Bound&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that the small sample size of this study means that it might have trouble detecting a statistically significant difference in diet change.  This study had a sample size of  623, with 178 having received a flyer.  The past Facebook study had a sample size of 104 and a similar leafleting study had a sample size of “about 500”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small changes in diet change can be drowned out by statistical noise.  To figure out what sample size we can use, we can use an “a priori sample size calculator for the two group chi-squared test”.  For this, we need a desired power level (chance of detecting the effect given that the effect exists), a probability level (our threshold p-value), and an estimate of the proportion of people who become vegetarians (or vegans, or reduce meat, etc.) in the control group and treatment group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any desired sample size is going to be a trade-off between wanting more statistical power and wanting to spend less money collecting the sample.  An additional consideration is that the desired sample size is the number of people we need to take the follow-up survey, which might be a smaller proportion of the total number of people that see the ads, due to inefficiencies in our conversion process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a table with some estimations with the classic probability level = 0.05 and desired power level = 0.8, and our treatment-control proportions found in this survey, here is how much larger our population would need to be to detect the effect with 80% chance, given our current study size and ratios between the treatment and control group:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Control %&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Treatment %&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Difference&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;Population Needed&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;8%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;+7%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;0.8x larger&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;+6%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1.01x larger&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;6%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;+5%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1.3x larger&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;5%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;+4%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1.7x larger&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;4%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;+3%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;2.5x larger&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;+2%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;4.4x larger&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;+1%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;12.4x larger&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;1.5%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;+0.5%&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td&gt;39.4x larger&lt;/td&gt;
	&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this table and our sample size, it’s possible that the leaflets could be converting people at a rate of 7% (relative to a 1% baseline) and we’d have about an 80% chance of detecting it. So therefore, I feel confidant placing a preliminary upper bound at 6%.  Based on this data, it’s highly unlikely that flyers convert at a rate higher than 6%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also of note is that if we think the difference between treatment and control is quite small (like 0.5%), we’d need a much larger study to detect it – 39.4x larger than our current study.  Though if we had an even split between treatment and control, it could be detected 80% of the time with just 16,294 people, or 26x our current population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-are-the-implications-for-aces-analysis&quot;&gt;What are the implications for ACE’s Analysis?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ACE concludes in their analysis that “[w]e found support for claims that distributing leaflets from Vegan Outreach (or similar leaflets published by other groups) causes a small percentage of respondents to go vegetarian or give up eating specific types of meat.”  This claim is tepid, but appears somewhat substantiated by my analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistical tests were able to connect the treatment flyers to the cessation of eating red meat and poultry, but these tests ceased to be statistically significant once Bonferroni corrections were made.  Additionally, they did not connect with any statistically significant finding for declared pescatarianism or meat reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, statistical tests were not able to reject the null hypothesis that leaflets do not cause wholesale shift to a vegetarian diet.  Therefore, the part of ACE’s claim that leaflets cause “a small percentage of respondents to go vegetarian” may not be established at this time.  However, less robust (but still plausibly reliable) were able to detect one person who responded as we would expect a vegetarian who had been changed by the leaflet to respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How bad is it that there was no connection between pescatarianism or meat reduction?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How bad is it that the tests were not able to pass Bonferroni corrections?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-are-the-implications-of-this-study-for-prior-studies-of-veg-outreach&quot;&gt;What are the implications of this study for prior studies of veg outreach?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s curious that this study finds a much smaller amount of vegetarian change attributable to flyers than a past study on leafleting, which found a conversion rate of 2% of leaflet takers becoming pescatarian (CCC Flyer Study), which is very similar to our study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Need for Some Point of Comparison, If Not a Control Group&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CCC Flyer Study sampled everyone, but only permitted those who received a leaflet to take the survey.  Of course, the language of the survey was strong, asking people to directly attribute their diet change to the leaflet.  But I imagine that this didn’t work as intended, and had they sampled people who did not receive the leaflet, or sampled at a college that had no leaflets distributed, it’s possible they would have found a similar conversion rate.  Therefore, it’s good that this study was done with ACE with a point of comparison, so we can see that the 2% figure does make sense in context.  Including these valuable pseudo-control groups is an important step forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recollection Errors&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior flyer research had attempted to navigate non-response bias (systematic biases in who fills out the survey) and social desirability bias (systematic increases in vegetarianism as people aim to please or look more virtuous).   Much has been done recently to try to work against these two biases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, another important aspect of the ACE Study is drawing our attention to a third form of bias – recollection errors.  ACE concludes that “[w]e do not know whether this pattern [of decreased meat consumption in our data] reflects real decreases in consumption or only systematic errors in recollection.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This recollection error also undermines the food frequency questionnaires used for meat reduction statistics – if they can’t remember receiving a leaflet, how can we trust them to remember intricate details about the number of servings of cheese they ate three months ago?  This seems difficult to deal with and suggests that new designs will be necessary for future studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How important is reducing red meat and poultry, but not anything else?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s certainly good that the leaflets are doing something, most notably getting about 4% of respondents to give up red meat and another 4% to give up poultry, with no corresponding increases in meat eating elsewhere.  But how important is this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my essay “How Much Suffering is in the Standard American Diet”, I provide figures that show if we take a suffering-per-kilogram point of view to our averting animal products, giving up red meat has 13% of the impact a typical vegan (not vegetarian) conversion would have, giving up poultry has 33.4% of the impact of veganism, and giving up both has 46% of the impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that a leaflet that converts 2% of people to become pescatarian (giving up red meat and poultry) would have essentially the same impact as a leaflet that converted 0.92% of people to become vegetarian, at least prima facie.  Given that these leaflets appear to have this impact on poultry elimination, that isn’t so bad!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vegetarian Recidivism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One potential problem, though, is that it’s unclear whether people would stick with poultry elimination with the same fervor as one would stick to vegetarianism.  It seems intuitively less likely to me, because there’s less of a culture and moral force surrounding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 100 Yard Line&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, perhaps we could look to Brian Tomasik’s 100 Yard Line Model for vegetarian conversion, which is summarized with the observation that perhaps pushing people to eliminate poultry and/or red meat is just one stepping stone to getting them to become full vegetarian soon.  It’s definitely a big first step!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why might the leaflets only be reducing red meat and poultry, and not other food groups?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the philosophical question about what the value of reducing red meat and poultry is, we might also be curious as to the empirical question – why are people only eliminating red meat and poultry, and not other food groups?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, we can only speculate, but it seems quite plausible that the reason is that the two treatment leaflets (“Compassionate Choices” and “Even if You Like Meat”) both focus significantly on the meat of pigs, chickens, and cows, and do not focus much at all on dairy, eggs, or fish.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/a-re-analysis-of-ace-leaflet-study/&quot;&gt;A Re-Analysis of ACE's Leaflet Study&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on June 04, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Much Suffering is in the Standard American Diet?]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/how-much-suffering-is-in-the-standard-american-diet/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/how-much-suffering-is-in-the-standard-american-diet</id>
  <published>2014-05-31T05:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-05-31T05:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We all know that “the standard American diet” is unhealthy, and bad for the environment, and all sorts of things.  But, as we know, it also contains a lot of suffering due to the consumption of factory-farmed meat.  I’m not going to argue for the ethics of a vegetarian diet here (&lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/why-eat-less-meat/&quot;&gt;I’ve done that elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;).  Instead, I’m interested in some quantification – just &lt;em&gt;how much&lt;/em&gt; suffering is in the standard American diet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a caveat, at the moment I’m not looking at environmental impact, though I might expand the analysis later.  As another caveat, it’s worth pointing out that the standard American diet may not really exist in any particular person, but it’s a useful statistical generalization to talk about.  As a third caveat, this analysis ignores the fact that there is an elasticity to supply and demand (e.g., by not eating one pound of cow, you do not cause precisely one pound of cow to not be produced, but rather just a large fraction of it, since a drop in demand leads to a corresponding drop in price, which leads to a corresponding yet smaller re-increase in demand.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin, we need to know three things: (a) how many animal products are in the standard american diet, (b) how many animals does it take to produce that much meat, and (c) how much suffering is brought about by each kind of animal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go! &lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;american-meat-consumption&quot;&gt;American Meat Consumption&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for us, the USDA is pretty obsessive with cataloging our food consumption.  The USDA’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/factbook/chapter2.pdf&quot;&gt;Profiling Food Consumption in America&lt;/a&gt; p15 says that in 2000, Americans consume, on average, per year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;64.4 pounds of beef&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;47.7 pounds of pork&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;52.9 pounds of poultry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;13.6 pounds of turkey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;15.2 pounds of fish and shellfish&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;250 eggs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;29.8 pounds of cheese&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;27.8 pounds of frozen dairy products (e.g., ice cream)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;22.6 pounds of milk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;animals-needed-to-produce-each-kind-of-meat&quot;&gt;Animals Needed to Produce Each Kind of Meat&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Brian Tomasik’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.utilitarian-essays.com/suffering-per-kg.html]&quot;&gt;“How Much Direct Suffering Is Caused by Various Animal Foods?”&lt;/a&gt;, Brian has a very similar goal to ours here, so we only need to extend his analysis to match up with the entire American diet, rather than individual animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian says that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…one beef cow produces 339kg of beef (747 pounds)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…one pig produces 91.1kg of pork (201 pounds)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…one meat chicken produces 1.83kg of poultry (4 pounds)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…one turkey produces 10.3kg of turkey meat (22.7 pounds)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…one egg chicken produces 15.3kg of eggs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…one dairy cow produces 50,420kg of milk (111,157 pounds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These numbers are good for our analysis, but a bit more work needs to be done to make the numbers work for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;eggs&quot;&gt;Eggs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, how many eggs is 15.3kg of eggs?  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicken_egg_sizes&quot;&gt;Wikipedia gives a list of egg sizes&lt;/a&gt;, and says that the typical egg is “large” sized, or 57g.  57g is 0.13 pounds, which means that 15.3kg of eggs (34 pounds) is 262 eggs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dairy&quot;&gt;Dairy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we know that dairy cows produce 50,420kg of milk, but what is that in terms of cheese and frozen dairy products?  If we could convert cheese and frozen dairy products into milk equivalents, we could make a cleaner calculation.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moomilk.com/faq/2-milk-faqs/35-how-many-pounds-of-milk-does-it-take-to-make-1-gallon-of-ice-cream-how-many-pounds-of-milk-does-it-take-to-make-1-pound-of-cheese&quot;&gt;The Moomilk FAQ&lt;/a&gt; pegs 1 gallon of ice cream at 12 pounds of milk and 1 pound of cheese at 10 pounds of milk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how much does a gallon of ice cream weigh?  Now we’ve descended to Wiki Answers (sorry!), but we come out with something: &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiki.answers.com/Q/How_much_does_one_gallon_of_ice_cream_weigh?#slide=2&quot;&gt;4.5 pounds&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we can take the 29.8 pounds of cheese and convert it to 298 pounds of milk equivalent.   Similarly, we can take the 27.8 pounds of frozen dairy products and convert it to 74 pounds of milk equivalent.  In total, that’s 394.6 pounds of milk per year for the average American.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fish&quot;&gt;Fish&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last, and the most troublesome, is working out fish.  14.2 pounds of fish and shellfish is not very helpful, because these animals are vastly different in sizes (and presumably suffering capacities).  For this analysis, I’m really only interested in factory farmed aquaculture fish, so I’ll switch over to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.countinganimals.com/how-many-animals-does-a-vegetarian-save/&quot;&gt;Counting Animal’s estimate&lt;/a&gt; of 1.3 aquacultured fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the aquaculturing of fish means that up to 225 wild fish are being caught to feed the aquacultured fish, but I’m uncomfortable including this number because I’m not sure that reducing the demand for fish will result in any significant reduction in suffering for wild fish.  While certainly fishing is painful for wild fish and there are great environmental concerns with overfishing, I’m choosing to not include them in this analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;american-animal-consumption&quot;&gt;American Animal Consumption&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have these statistics, we can find out not how many pounds of animal meat is consumed each year by a typical American, but rather &lt;em&gt;how many animals are consumed&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;drumroll please…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.09 cows for beef&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.004 cows for dairy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.24 pigs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;13.2 chickens for meat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.95 chickens for egg&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.6 turkeys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.3 aquacultured fish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-how-much-suffering-is-that&quot;&gt;But How Much Suffering is That?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously quantifying suffering is very tricky, so I’m going to be careful about it here.  Stay with me.  Let’s first look to how many days of suffering each animal undergoes, sort of like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disability-adjusted_life_year&quot;&gt;DALY metric&lt;/a&gt; would do for quantifying suffering in humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking to Brian’s table, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.utilitarian-essays.com/suffering-per-kg.html#section4&quot;&gt;we get the following information&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cows for beef live 402 days on average&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cows for dairy = 2009 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pigs = 183 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chickens for meat = 42 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chickens for eggs = 365 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turkeys = 126 days&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aquacultured fish = 730 days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the average American is producing, each year on average…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;36 days of suffering via beef&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8 days of suffering via dairy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;44 days of suffering via pork&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;554 days of suffering via chicken meat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;347 days of suffering via eggs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;76 days of suffering via turkey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;949 days of suffering via aquacultured fish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…That means there’s a total of 5 years, 6 months, 5 days of animal suffering in each standard American diet, &lt;strong&gt;per year&lt;/strong&gt;.  Yikes!  …And this doesn’t even include the suffering from the slaughter of the animals themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adjusting-for-context&quot;&gt;Adjusting for Context&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we can get a bit more precise at the cost of being a bit more speculative, if you don’t mind me experimenting, because I don’t think that each animal suffers the same.  Instead, each animal has (a) different intensity of farming conditions and (b) a different capacity for suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s do differences from intensity of farming conditions.  Brian’s table takes this into account, and suggests the following adjustment ratios (higher ratio means more suffering from the farming):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beef - 1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dairy - 1.8&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pork - 1.8&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chicken (meat) - 1.8&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chicken (eggs) - 2.5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turkey - 1.8&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aquacultured Fish - 0.9&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like more research into this, but right now I’m willing for Brian’s work to be taken at face value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we need some estimates of the differences of capacity to suffer.  Again, these are just my rough intuitions, should not be taken at face value, and can be easily disagreed with.  Feel free to substitute your own numbers.  I arrive at these ratios (higher ratio means more capcacity for suffering):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beef - 1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dairy - 1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pork - 1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chicken (meat) - 0.3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chicken (eggs) - 0.3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Turkey - 0.3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aquacultured Fish - 0.2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking these ratios into account, we adjust to the new totals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;36 adjusted days of suffering via beef&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14 adjusted days of suffering via dairy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;79 adjusted days of suffering via pork&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;299 adjusted days of suffering via chicken meat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;260 adjusted days of suffering via eggs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;41 adjusted days of suffering via turkey&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;171 adjusted days of suffering via aquacultured fish 	900&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The adjustment is technically in units of “days of beef suffering equivalents”.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;relative-importance&quot;&gt;Relative Importance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these adjustments are important not for coming to a more accurate total of years of suffering caused per year of American diet, but rather for more accurately determining which food groups are the most important to target.  For example, based on these adjusted numbers, we can tentatively (and perhaps naively) conclude:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Giving up beef is ~2.6x as important as giving up dairy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Giving up pork is ~2.2x as important as giving up beef.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Giving up chicken meat is ~8.3x as important as giving up beef.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Giving up eggs is ~7.2x as important as giving up beef.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Giving up turkey is ~1.1x as important as giving up beef.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Giving up aquacultured fish is ~4.8x as important as giving up beef.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this gives a pretty good approach for a “meat reduction” diet, with the most ethical bang-for-the-buck for each animal product given up.  Maybe consider eating all the beef, turkey, and dairy you want, but spare the really important ones – chicken, eggs, and fish!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, a diet where you only avoid chicken, eggs, and fish is 81% as impactful at preventing animal suffering as a fully vegan diet!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/how-much-suffering-is-in-the-standard-american-diet/&quot;&gt;How Much Suffering is in the Standard American Diet?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on May 31, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sunday Links #27]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-27/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-27</id>
  <published>2014-05-25T05:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-05-25T05:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Meta-note: I’ve now decided that I like shifting toward doing these less frequently, with less links each, but in much more depth, potentially spinning more lengthy discussion to my Tumblr.  Going forward, I will now also tag each of these posts with “Sunday Links” &lt;i&gt;in addition to&lt;/i&gt; tagging them with the categories of the contained links, when appropriate.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Longer musing redirected to my Tumblr: &lt;a href=&quot;http://peterhurford.tumblr.com/post/86722676721/not-all-arguments-are-nuanced&quot;&gt;“Not All Arguments are Nuanced”&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Sometimes I hear my non-Greek female friends talk about men in fraternities being rapists, or even more likely to rape than the typical person. This has always made me uncomfortable, even if it is technically true. I always feel tempted to say “But not all Greek men are like that”, a variation on the clichéd &lt;a href=&quot;http://knowyourmeme.com/memes/not-all-men-are-like-that&quot;&gt;Not All Men Are Like That&lt;/a&gt; you hear in feminist circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Of course, this type of derailment is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vox.com/2014/5/15/5720332/heres-why-women-have-turned-the-not-all-men-objection-into-a-meme&quot;&gt;appropriately rejected for reasons Vox explains well&lt;/a&gt;, which is why I say it in my head and not in real life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But I’m still uncomfortable.  I know it’s not all about me, but it’s how I feel as a participant in the discussion.  I feel uncomfortable and now I understand why.&amp;lt;/blockquote&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another musing redicted to Tumblr, this time about politics: &lt;a href=&quot;http://peterhurford.tumblr.com/post/86762672854/why-are-politicians-crazy-one-potential-theory&quot;&gt;“Why Are Politicians Crazy?: One Potential Theory”&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There’s a fundamental paradox with some politicians: they’re smart enough to get law degrees from top universities, start a multi-million dollar political campaign, fund and sustain a multi-million dollar political campaign, and win a multi-million dollar political campaign, yet… some of these politicians are crazy.  …Like off-the-wall crazy with their ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It presumably takes a lot of talent to start and win a political campaign.  So how can these crazy politicians be so crazy yet so smart?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The dominant theory is one of multiple intelligences – they’re talented at being likable and attracting money, but not good at generating useful policy.  The runner-up theory is that winning a campaign is much easier than I’m giving it credit for.  (Though why people who are also talented at policy don’t win an easy campaign is beyond me.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But I like a third theory.  I call it the “Secret Smarts” theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott Alexander writes that we should &lt;a href=&quot;http://slatestarcodex.com/2014/05/08/vote-on-values-outsource-beliefs/&quot;&gt;“Vote on Values, Outsource Beliefs”&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today I learned about social impact bonds. […] The basic idea is: government could save a lot of money if some problem got fixed. For example, if people stopped committing crime, they could spend less money on prisons. So they make a deal with a corporation. The corporation agrees to spend a certain amount of money to prevent crime for five years. And if crime goes down and the government saves on prisons, the corporation gets half the savings (or a third, or whatever).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Zero taxpayer money gets risked. It is entirely up to the corporation to fund the problem-solving effort. If they fail, then it’s their own loss. If they succeed, then the government pays them money, but less than the government made, so the taxpayers still get a profit. […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The particular article I read about this today was How Goldman Sachs Can Get Paid To Keep People Out Of Jail. It was the name “Goldman Sachs” that got me excited. They’re an investment bank. Their job is predicting risk. I don’t know if they’re any good at it or not. But they’re the sort of organization that potentially could be. So we have people who understand risk trying to figure out what social policies will produce which results, with money riding on the decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is looking impressively close to prediction markets. Futarchy says “vote on values, bet on beliefs”. Asking a corporation to invest money in crime-solving is a form of betting on belief – they are betting on what anti-crime programs will decrease crime most and win them the most reward. You still have the elected government deciding what bonds to place – voting on values – but you’re outsourcing your beliefs to the corporation involved and giving them an incentive to get it right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Think of all the possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a game called &lt;a href=&quot;http://superhotgame.com/&quot;&gt;Super Hot&lt;/a&gt;.  It’s part puzzle and part shooter.  You have to deal with limited ammo and a refreshingly realistic one shot kills you, but you’re not stressed as you get enough time to think about your strategy and your shots.  In the end, you get to run around as some sort of (refreshingly unrealistic) super ninja.  (Robin Hanson and Jesse Galef &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.overcomingbias.com/2014/05/first-person-em-shooter.html&quot;&gt;think the shooter is like what life would be like as a computer emulated brain&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been having a bit too much fun with this.  Right now &lt;a href=&quot;http://superhotgame.com/play-prototype&quot;&gt;it can be played in the browser&lt;/a&gt;, but there’s also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/375798653/superhot&quot;&gt;A Kickstarter&lt;/a&gt; for a full version of the game (already fully funded, but they’re working toward some cooler additional things).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some satire on the idea of pitching effective altruism, from Michael Bitton: &lt;a href=&quot;http://a-nice-place-to-live.blogspot.ca/2014/04/the-worlds-worst-meme.html&quot;&gt;The World’s Worst Meme&lt;/a&gt;.  Maybe “self-sacrifice” is not a big seller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In related news, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.benkuhn.net/outreach&quot;&gt;Ben Kuhn writes some reflection about effective altruism outreach gathered from running “Harvard Effective Altruism” for two years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of effective altruism, here’s a good real life example: should Detroit sell off masterpieces in the local art museum to help stabalize the finances of the city?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/30/business/economy/costs-benefits-and-masterpieces-in-detroit.html?ref=business&amp;amp;_r=0&quot;&gt;Robert Frank says the answer is yes&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Consider “The Wedding Dance,” a 16th-century work by the Flemish painter Pieter Bruegel the Elder. Detroit museum visitors have enjoyed this painting since 1930. How much would it cost to preserve that privilege for future generations?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A tidy sum, as it turns out. According to Christie’s, this canvas alone could fetch up to $200 million. Once interest rates return to normal levels — say, 6 percent — the forgone interest on that amount would be approximately $12 million a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If we assume that the museum would be open 2,000 hours a year, and ignore the cost of gallery space and other indirect expenses, the cost of keeping the painting on display would be more than $6,000 an hour. Assuming that an average of five people would view it per hour, all year long, it would still cost more than $1,200 an hour to provide the experience for each visitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;http://slatestarcodex.com/2014/04/21/the-economics-of-art-and-the-art-of-economics/&quot;&gt;Scott Alexander puts it:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So the question of “should Detroit keep this painting?” reduces to “does the average visitor to the art museum derive $1200 in value from seeing this particular painting?” which is very close to “would you pay $1200 for a ticket to an art museum that only had this painting in it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…Case settled to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-27/&quot;&gt;Sunday Links #27&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on May 25, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Review for March - May 2014]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/personal-review-for-march-may-2014/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/personal-review-for-march-may-2014</id>
  <published>2014-05-20T05:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-05-20T05:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Follow up to &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/personal-review-for-december-2013-february-2014/&quot;&gt;“Personal Review for December 2013 - February 2014”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m doing this review a little bit earlier because (a) I just graduated college and feel like I want to review what I’ve done within that context and (b) I can get back onto a Jan-Mar, Apr-Jun, Jul-Sep, Oct-Dec review cycle by doing a May-Jun review next.  I’ve also had a shift in goals that fits well within this cycle as I start work at the beginning of July.  This review covers 1 Mar to 17 May. &lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-i-spend-my-time&quot;&gt;How Did I Spend My Time?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two months, I was focused on pre-professional prep (learning a lot more statistics and programming), bringing greater organization to my projects, and trying different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Activity&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;Hours Per Week&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;Per Day&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;% of Day&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;% of Awake Day&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sleep&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;54.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;7.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;32%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Friends&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;35.0&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;21%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;31%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other[1]&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;24.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3.5&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;15%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;22%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Programming&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;17.2&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.5&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;15%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Break&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;12.5&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Class[2]&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;5.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;5%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Beta&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;4.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;4%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Exercise&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.5&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;.impact&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3.0&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.5&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Write&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.5&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Senior Research&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.9&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;DVP&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.2&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;DCA&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.2&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;ACE&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.1&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;80K&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.4&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.05&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1: Other includes things like showering, hygeine, prioritizing tasks, reading/answering email, travelling, packing/unpacking, visiting the dentist, getting a haircut, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2: Class does not include my Computer Science class, which was instead included in Programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-i-accomplish-pre-professional-prep&quot;&gt;What Did I Accomplish?: Pre-professional Prep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent 17.2 hours a week (189.3 hours total) learning programming, which is almost a part time job.  This was broken down with 89.8 hours (47.4%) spent on my CS class (Python, C++); 48 hours (25%) redesigning all my websites (lots of CSS, some JavaScript); 28.8 hours (15.2%) spent developing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jorgestradingpost.com&quot;&gt;Jorge’s Trading Post&lt;/a&gt; (PHP); 10.5 hours (5.5%) learning R; 6.5 hours (3.4%) learning Ruby/Rails; and 6 hours (3%) on other miscellaneous stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy with this level of time commitment, but I would like to up it both in overall quantity and in distribution.  As my job will be working with Ruby/Rails and R, I need to spend the vast majority of my time focusing on those two languages.  I’d ideally like to work 40 hours a week on learning programming to make sure I’m prepared, which would give me another 240 hours of prep, which I think would be adequate, especially if focused on Ruby/Rails and R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-i-accomplish-ea-projects&quot;&gt;What Did I Accomplish?: EA Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to focusing on pre-professional prep, I was also focused on expanding my knowledge of EA Projects by trying a bunch out and seeing how things went, with the goal of finding opportunities to focus in on.  My overall goal was to try to make some progress in six areas: marketing/outreach, community building, cause prioritization research, coaching, and project management.  Here’s how I’ve done so far:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;marketing--outreach&quot;&gt;Marketing / Outreach&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UKX_xzUGEcI&quot;&gt;TEDx Talk&lt;/a&gt; on 1 Mar.  It was viewed in person by about 200 people and then viewed online by 260 more people.  It’s too difficult to figure out how many people were influenced by it.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/effective-altruism-at-tedxdenisonu/&quot;&gt;I wrote a retrospective&lt;/a&gt; that I think is informative for helping develop the pitch for EA.  Overall, I spent 34.3 hours preparing, giving, and reviewing the TEDx event.  I don’t think the talk had much impact, though I’ll continue to monitor.  It was worth the experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/conversation-with-michael-bitton-about-ea-marketing/&quot;&gt;a conversation with Michael Bitton&lt;/a&gt; where we discussed EA marketing, including the promising idea of focusing on atheists / skeptics, currently being explored by the new organization &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.charityscience.com&quot;&gt;Charity Science&lt;/a&gt; (though I believe they thought of targeting that group independently).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;community-building&quot;&gt;Community Building&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/interview-with-boris-yakubchik/&quot;&gt;interviewed Boris Yakubchik&lt;/a&gt;.  The benefit here is to use human stories to inspire people into effective altruism.  A few people said they found the interview useful, though it’s hard to know how much impact this translates into.  This took 3.5 hours of my time and two hours of Boris’s time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cause-prioritization-research&quot;&gt;Cause Prioritization Research&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did some more research on the cost-effectiveness of vegetarian advocacy (currently unpublished).  More by the next review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;coaching&quot;&gt;Coaching&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/learn-code/&quot;&gt;a guide on how to learn programming&lt;/a&gt;.  Six people told me personally that they would use it.  I still have not checked in with any of them, but intend to do so before the next review.  This took me five hours of my time and one hour of other people’s time.  More on the impact of this by the next review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I coached one person in productivity techniques, but still haven’t followed up enough to know if I’ve had any impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also coached two people on how to add effective altruism into one’s life.  For one person, I think I had an impact, but I’m very confident that this person counterfactually would have turned out the same if I had not coached her.  For the second person, I have still not followed up as there hasn’t been enough time.  More on this in the next review.  Both of these coaching sessions were one hour each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I coached two people in career choice.  For one, I don’t think I’ll have any impact.  For &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/career-advice-for-phyllis-schmidt-choosing-between-masters-programming-and-direct-work&quot;&gt;the other&lt;/a&gt;, it’s too soon to see if I’ll have any impact.  These took 1.5 hours of my time, each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I reached out to Jacy to review &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/career-advice-for-jacy-choosing-between-ph-d-programs/&quot;&gt;the impact of my prior coaching with him&lt;/a&gt;.  It appears my advice did not have any direct impact, but “the social support/encouragement of having another like-minded individual in a similar place in life accomplishing visible [and] productive” was “most important”.  Likewise, Jacy felt inspired by how I “took a non-standard career path (AFAIK, you’re doing EtG+Movement-Building, which is pretty unique) and that probably galvanized [his] decision to do a similar thing with graduate school (career capital+Movement-Building)”.  The advice plus the review was two hours of my time, so I think it was worth it.  Overall, careers coaching seems to be a promising use of my time, even if I have not generated any career changes.  More by the next review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;project-management&quot;&gt;Project Management&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I re-started &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dotimpact.im/&quot;&gt;.impact&lt;/a&gt; after a month hiatus.  While three of our members (Ozzie Gooen, Patrick Brinich-Langois, and Ciaran Phillips) have dramatically scaled down their time commitment for .impact in order to pursue finding a programming job, we’ve added two new committed members – Tom Ash and Jacy Anthis – who have started work on different projects, most notably &lt;a href=&quot;http://effectivealtruismhub.com/survey&quot;&gt;a survey of effective altruists&lt;/a&gt; (take it if you haven’t already) and several community building tools, such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://effectivealtruismhub.com/map&quot;&gt;a map of EAs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://effectivealtruismhub.com/donations&quot;&gt;a cause-neutral donation registry&lt;/a&gt;.  I don’t think my project management or project work here is essential, but it seems somewhat critical, so it appears to be 34 hours well invested during this review cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eating-and-exercise&quot;&gt;Eating and Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, I said I would have to renew my focus to eating right and exercising consistently for the next review cycle.  I have done this to some success by committing to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.beeminder.com&quot;&gt;Beeminder&lt;/a&gt;, which tracks your goals and charge you money for derailing.  This allowed me to regain my ability to run a 5k in about half an hour (10min mile).  I also boosted my Squat, but none of my other lifts – Squat +10lbs (215 to 225lbs), Benchpress +0lbs (110lbs), Deadlift +0lbs (265lbs), Overhead Press +0lbs (85lbs), and Rows +0lbs (110lbs).  I owe this letdown to the smaller review cycle and the fact that not exercising for a large period of time lead me to have to spend my time catching up rather than increasing my lifts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Beeminder, I also have been able to more frequently keep to a healthy diet and eat significantly less junk food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goals-for-the-next-review&quot;&gt;Goals for the Next Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My three-year goal is to watch the development of the effective altruist community and my own personal talents to (a) assess how much room there is for marginal high-impact EA projects work, (b) assess whether I would be well suited for that work personally, and (c) assess whether doing that work full-time would be preferable to working full-time and donating some of my salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m only 1.5 months in, but it appears that coaching, project management, and cause prioritization research have some promise (listed in decending order of promise-having).  I’m also reasonably confident they could amount to full-time work.  However, I’m still very uncertain whether my working full-time on this area would be better than my ability to donate potentially $30K-$40K a year and rising to other people already working in the area, like the Centre for Effective Altruism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my next review cycle (now until the beginning of July, right after I settle into my new job), &lt;strong&gt;I’ll be taking a bit of a different approach and focusing as much as I can on learning programming to prepare for my job.&lt;/strong&gt;  Originally, I was also planning on focusing on EA Projects, but I expect that marginal time learning programming will be more immediately valuable for increasing my near-term and long-term job prospects.  Furthermore, as I home after college, I expect to be allocating a significant amount of time to seeing my friends, family, and girlfriend prior to entering the “real world”.  As you can see, I already spent 35 hours a week with friends over the past two months, celebrating the end of college.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/personal-review-for-march-may-2014/&quot;&gt;Personal Review for March - May 2014&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on May 20, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conversation with Michael Bitton about EA Marketing]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/conversation-with-michael-bitton-about-ea-marketing/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/conversation-with-michael-bitton-about-ea-marketing</id>
  <published>2014-05-10T13:20:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-05-10T13:20:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Michael Bitton is a graduate student in Media Production in Toronto. For his thesis paper, he’s been researching effective uses of media for doing good in the world. He currently sees the most potential in health communication and social marketing in the developing world.  You can find out about his writings at his blog, &lt;a href=&quot;http://a-nice-place-to-live.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;A Nice Place to Live&lt;/a&gt;.  I had &lt;a href=&quot;https://impact.hackpad.com/Conversation-with-Michael-Bitton-26-Feb-2014-bfP047Kgt3v&quot;&gt;this conversation with him on 26 Feb&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dotimpact.im/&quot;&gt;.impact&lt;/a&gt;, but thought it would be good to cross-post the conversation here.  I’ve added a bit more from the comments I’ve received from others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: These notes are a quick summary of our conversation and may not be all that coherent.  They miss a lot of nuance and may not reflect statements that both people agree to. &lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-goal-of-marketing-ea&quot;&gt;What is the goal of marketing EA?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Move more existing donations to more effective charities&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create more donations&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get more people to think of “doing good” as a consideration for choosing their career&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create more people who will identify as effective altruists?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create more vegetarians / vegans?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-could-the-target-audience-be&quot;&gt;Who could the target audience be?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;generally-speaking&quot;&gt;Generally Speaking…&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, it seems like people either get EA immediately or not, as seen in currently unpublished GWWC marketing surveys.  Though, as Ben Kuhn points out, this could be confabulation. He wouldn’t be surprised if people edited their memories so that they “got it” immediately.  Ben used to think that he “got it immediately”, but now says in retrospect he doesn’t think that’s true.  I personally think I got it immediately, even in retrospect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pablo Stafforini says that this could be tested by considering the lag between exposure to EA material and affiliation to an EA org, as it’s much harder to confabulate dates than about thought processes. Anecdotally, Pablo says he knows of many people who decided to contact GWWC and even sign the pledge after a few days of reading The Life You Can Save.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Bitton thinks that equating “EA” with “signing GWWC’s pledge” is setting the bar way too high and that the bulk of the untapped population would only be persuaded to give “part-way.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fine-tuning-the-message&quot;&gt;Fine Tuning the Message&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it’s true that there is a core group of people that will get it, reaching them is all that is important (“spray and pray” method), though we should check o make sure this isn’t misguided.  It’s also possible that if we fine-tune our message, we can reach more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GWWC is a really big ask, and people might be receptive to smaller asks, like The Life You Can Save – comparing asking people to pledge at different rates would be informative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core EAs in Switzerland think that getting interested in science/rationality first may be more effective than pitching altruism. This works better for them and is their new strategy. Adriano Mannino knows more about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;potential-target-group-secularist--atheist--skeptic-community&quot;&gt;Potential Target Group: Secularist / Atheist / Skeptic community&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Interested in secular morality&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Friendly to consequentialism&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Friendly to applying skepticism to charity&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Friendly to thinking rationally / hearing arguments&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Niel Bowerman thinks this would be a great group to tap into more heavily.  His intuition is that many of them would “get” effectiveness and convincing them of the altruism component wouldn’t be all that difficult.  He would be interested in hearing from anyone who has tried approaching these communities in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;potential-target-group-devoutly-religious&quot;&gt;Potential Target Group: Devoutly religious&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pre-existing drive toward altruism&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Willing to tithe their income / donate lots&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;May not identify with EA directly, but maybe a church could be persuaded to donate to Against Malaria Foundation or Give Directly, though it may be hard to persuade them away from religious / local causes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Downside: the religious tend to be unfriendly to consequentialism&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Niel knows a few very dedicated EA pursuing earning-to-give that have come through this route.  Like other groups such as campaigners that are already heavily bought into the idea of altruism, my experience is that a much lower fraction are interested, but for the very few who ‘get’ EA they can become very dedicated.  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-our-pitch&quot;&gt;What is our pitch?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emphasize an “excited altruism” approach.&lt;/strong&gt;  While lots of current EAs found the moral-imperative approach compelling, the intuition is that a message of “self-sacrifice” might not be catchy for the mainstream.  But it would be good to test further.  Michael Bitton think people are driven mostly by low motives and thus their decisions will come down to factors besides merely identifying the morally right action. Plenty of people think vegetarianism is the morally superior option and yet eat meat anyway.  Furthermore, the existence of current moral-imperative-EAs is much evidence that that pitch would persuade more people. It could be that the moral-imperative-people would naturally be the first ones to join, for some reason. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gather more stories of people who are EAs.&lt;/strong&gt;  Emphasizing a human element might make it more appealing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concern that EA as community might backfire.&lt;/strong&gt;  Bitton says that people don’t like joining communities that have a value system.  Furthermore, other things in the ea community could be a turn-off to some people.  While the connection to utilitarianism is ok, things like cryonics, transhumanism, insect suffering, AGI, eugenics, whole brain emulation, suffering subroutines, the cost-effectiveness of having kids, polyamory, intelligence-enhancing drugs, the ethics of terraforming, bioterrorism, nanotechnology, synthetic biology, mindhacking, etc. might not appeal well.  There’s a chance that people might accept the more mainstream global poverty angle, but be turned off by other aspects of EA.  Bitton is unsure whether this is meant to be a reason for de-emphasizing these other aspects of the movement.  Obviously, we want to attract more people, but also people that are more EA.  He doesn’t have a good sense of how to approach decisions that involve trade-offs between these two desiderata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider the fanbase analogy.&lt;/strong&gt;  As a start, Bitton thinks the above concern should be treated as analogous to a corporation deciding whether to appease its core fan base or the (more numerous) casual fans. I’m more interested in gaining “casual fans” (ordinary people that start to give a bit more or decide a bit better) than in further uniting the “core fan base” (the people that currently post in EA Facebook groups, on LessWrong, identify as EAs, read EA blogs, work on EA projects, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concern the EA community is too homogonous.&lt;/strong&gt; Even if EA is not a value system or ideology, it’s still a somewhat clear identity category (white, atheist, background in STEM, rationalist, “nerdy,” introverted, familiar with philosophy, dislike of continental philosophy, “innocent” in the sense of low rates of tattoos, piercings, smoking, heavy drinking, radical physical appearance, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Need more on-the-ground research to figure out how normal people think of charity&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g., people donate to cancer charities because their parents died of cancer).  Perhaps it would be immediately obvious that saving lives is more important than the arts, but people haven’t realized the things are in tension…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Need to learn more about what pitches work&lt;/strong&gt; through A-B testing, focus groups, talk with marketers, etc., to create actionable findings that are generally useful for the whole movement.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/conversation-with-michael-bitton-about-ea-marketing/&quot;&gt;Conversation with Michael Bitton about EA Marketing&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on May 10, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview with Boris Yakubchik]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/interview-with-boris-yakubchik/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/interview-with-boris-yakubchik</id>
  <published>2014-05-07T02:46:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-05-07T02:46:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some people have committed a great deal of their lives to trying to best make the world a better place. I’m trying to sit down with some of these people and learn more about their thoughts and motivations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I sit down with Boris Yakubchik.  He’s the co-President of Giving What We Can: Rutgers and has been involved in the effective altruist movement for a long time, regularly giving away 50% of his income to the Against Malaria Foundation. &lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/images/posts/interview-with-boris-yakubchik/boris.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Boris Yakubchik&quot; title=&quot;Boris Yakubchik&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peter Hurford:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;One of the most notable things about you is that you regularly give 50% of your salary to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.againstmalaria.com&quot;&gt;the Against Malaria Foundation&lt;/a&gt; without missing a beat.  How did you get to that point in your life?  And do you plan on going any further?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boris Yakubchik:&lt;/strong&gt; I was lucky to have learned about effective altruism before I started my full-time job. I joined &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givingwhatwecan.org/&quot;&gt;Giving What We Can&lt;/a&gt; previously and was already giving 10% from my part-time self-employed tutoring income. And by January 2012 I started my full-time job as a high-school math teacher and my income more-than-doubled. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before taxes I started earning close-to $50,000 and my expenses were less than $20,000. I figured I didn’t need a more-lavish lifestyle and I thought I would be able to sustain giving 50% to cost-effective charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately in 2013 I was not working full time and wanted to quickly pay down the college debt of my fiancée, so I temporarily decreased my giving to 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m at the moment trying out a work-from-home business in which my parents have been successful; it has the potential for a significantly higher income than a teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Why did you pick Against Malaria Foundation as a place to give?  Why not give somewhere else, or to a bunch of different charities?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; At the time that I started giving, AMF was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givewell.org/&quot;&gt;GiveWell&lt;/a&gt;’s top-rated charity.  I feel that is the best reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I had several “Birthday for Charity” events and was able to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.againstmalaria.com/Fundraiser.aspx?FundraiserID=6941&quot;&gt;raise money for AMF directly through their website&lt;/a&gt;. There is certainly a psychological tie to giving to AMF because I’ve publicly endorsed AMF for several years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m open to giving to other charities, and through the years have done that. Specifically I gave to &lt;a href=&quot;http://veganoutreach.org/&quot;&gt;Vegan Outreach&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thehumaneleague.com/&quot;&gt;the Humane League&lt;/a&gt; based on the evaluations from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalcharityevaluators.org/&quot;&gt;Animal Charity Evaluators&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some strong arguments that conclude that once you find the best charity, you ought to give there. I give the bulk of my money to whichever charity I think does the most towards eliminating extreme poverty, but will continue to give nontrivial amounts to organizations that effectively decrease animal suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;You say your expenses are less than $20K.  That’s quite frugal!  How do you make that work?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; I don’t want lavish things, my car is for purposes of getting from point A to point B. I try to minimize large expenses (like apartment rent). I rarely eat out (my fiancee cooks amazing food). Most of the entertainment is virtually free: spending time with friends, reading book and internet, watching films at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote up some of the best advice about frugal liging that I’ve come across on my website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yboris.com/frugal.php&quot;&gt;http://www.yboris.com/frugal.php&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Let’s change topics a little bit.  Another thing I’ve seen you talk a lot about is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/GivingWhatWeCanRutgers&quot;&gt;Giving What We Can chapter at Rutgers&lt;/a&gt;.  What does it do?  And how did you get involved with it?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; I was lucky to watch the Rutgers chapter get started (primarily by Nick Beckstead, Mark Lee, and Tim Campbell) and attend the meetings from day one. At our second meeting I gave a short talk about positive psychology and how giving affects happiness (primarily relying on Andreas Mogensen’s wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givingwhatwecan.org/sites/givingwhatwecan.org/files/attachments/giving-without-sacrifice.pdf&quot;&gt;“Giving Without Sacrifice”&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the second academic year I volunteered (and was elected) as the president. The main task has been to organize events, and get others involved. The primary function of the chapter is to draw an audience of undergraduate and graduate students, educate them about the problems of extreme world poverty, and demonstrate to them that they can individually make a big positive difference in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve done that through a variety of events like lectures (e.g. Poverty: Lessons Learned from Photography), workshops (e.g. THINK’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thehighimpactnetwork.org/modules/charity-assessment&quot;&gt;Evaluating Social Interventions&lt;/a&gt;), and fundraising (Booksale for Charity). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last academic year we had another President running Giving What We Can: Rutgers, Michaél MF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Wow.  I always forget that there are a lot of cool people involved in the Rutgers chapter!  Have your events been able to engage people well?  What lessons have you learned from running them?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; I wish I tracked our success more quantitatively, but I’m confident that over the years we’ve been able to encourage many to start giving more effectively. At the very least, several of my friends have joined Giving What We Can (started giving at least 10%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the events we had, for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Dsl9cyaIn-g&quot;&gt;Thomas Pogge came to give a talk&lt;/a&gt;, drew an audience of students who have never heard of Giving What We Can, several stayed around after the talk to learn more. Some events were attended poorly, in part because of poor advertizing on my part, but we have video recordings for others to see, for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RvUcbcUMtXw&quot;&gt;Zell Kravinsky talked about how he gave away over $40 million&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s certainly important to have an interesting and educational event, it’s very important to advertise widely. Doing things by yourself isn’t the best strategy, I really recommend giving specific tasks to those who are interested in helping (e.g. contact the student paper to send a correspondent, or print 3 flyers and post them in these buildings).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Do you have any tips on how to advertise an event so that people get interested and come?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; I’m not sure how important it is to have a well-designed flyers, but posting flyers has been successful for us. There have been times when we post flyers on the day of the event with “TODAY” written on it. I think that can encourage more people to look at the flyer, thus increasing the chances of more people attending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal invitations have worked well, one acquaintance I had I urged to come to our meeting, she came just because of the request and was interested enough to come to many events for several semesters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had better success getting people to come when I was a student at Rutgers. I don’t know, but it seemed that when we had weekly meetings (same day, same time, same location), we had better attendance than when we had them bi-weekly. Perhaps building a habit is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;I saw that as a part of GWWC: Rutgers you even were able to give a TEDx talk on cost-effectiveness in philanthropy.  That’s so cool!  How did you arrange for that to happen?  What came out of it?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; TEDxRutgers happened for several years at Rutgers and in early 2013, Michaél MF told me that he knew some of the people organizing the event. Because I’ve given talks related to Effective Altruism (some modeled on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HcZkXq2C40I&quot;&gt;Toby Ord’s presentation&lt;/a&gt;), Michaél put me in touch with the organizers. I was lucky that they still had some space in their line-up and I was accepted with a 12-minute limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had significant help from friends and the EA community while drafting and revising my talk (at the very least I’d like to thank Roxanne Heston). I wish I had an extra day to practice, because during the final talk I stumbled several times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it took a long time for the video to be edited.  But,finally, a year later, we were able to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DPe9-OM7vgU&quot;&gt;post it online on the Giving What We Can YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;In addition to raising awareness via Giving What We Can: Rutgers, I’ve also seen you raise awareness on different issues via prolific posting on Facebook.  And I remember we once talked about how you were handing out leaflets from Vegan Outreach that encourage people to eat less meat.  A lot of people, like me, care a lot about these causes, but are too shy to become activists.  How did you cross that bridge?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; I was rather shy even in my first year in college, but by third year I became a lot more social (with the help of a friend who kept encouraging me to go to parties with him). I didn’t like the parties, but at some point I somehow knew hundreds of people and felt a lot more confident talking to strangers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I went silly in the head on Facebook and started befriending people who I just met once, or who had some large number of friends in common; so I managed to have a ‘network’ of about a thousand people. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I was a cheerleader for science, posting news of fantastic discoveries and potential technologies, but with time, especially once I learned of extreme world poverty and moral arguments like Peter Singer’s, I decided to use my platform to share pro-social ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think incremental steps can help one become less uneasy about approaching others (when handing out VO booklets), and it’s easy to talk about what you’re passionate about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Do you have any recommendations to people that also want to get involved in influencing, whether through Facebook, pamphlets, or official organizations?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; Facebook provides a rather safe environment for starting a conversation. It’s hard to know how much influence posts and discussions can have, but I think over the years, at least a dozen people have messaged me privately saying things akin to “I really appreciate your posts” and even “You’ve influenced my thinking”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve occasionally posted images that were provoking (especially ones urging people to take steps to decrease animal suffering). Sometimes the discussions are hijacked by people that sound like they are from another planet, but at other times it feels productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting involved with official organizations is great because they legitimize what you are doing. It’s much easier to talk about a topic when others are there for that purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Has anyone reacted negatively or hostile to your activism?  If so, how do you deal with that?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve had in the past some discussions with friends (in person) where the topic of morality came up and I argued too forcefully. I think one needs to be very careful when discussing issues like that because even well-worded comments can be misunderstood, and even the purpose of the discussion could be misinterpreted. With practice you can get better at these conversations. I absolutely love Giving What We Can’s approach: you just share your excitement about how awesome it is that you can, thanks to research and awesome organizations, help people significantly with little cost to you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s possible that some people won’t be moved by arguments or other appeals. Something that’s helpful is to keep in mind that people come from different backgrounds with different assumptions. Motivating a change that is too drastic can backfire. Reading books written by psychologist can help (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Influence-Psychology-Persuasion-Business-Essentials/dp/006124189X&quot;&gt;Influence&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Charisma-Myth-Personal-Magnetism/dp/1591845947&quot;&gt;The Charisma Myth&lt;/a&gt;, etc)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most helpful books I’ve read was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/The-Animal-Activists-Handbook-Maximizing/dp/1590561201&quot;&gt;“The Animal Activist’s Handbook”&lt;/a&gt; which shares excellent (psychology-informed) advice about working towards change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Speaking of vegan activism, I’ve heard you describe yourself personally as “near vegan”.  What do you mean by that?  And how did you make that lifestyle change?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; The first time I heard of vegetarianism was with a PETA leaflet that compared factory farms with concentration camps. This was too-drastic for me to accept at the time and I promptly threw it away with a laugh and a thought “crazy people”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was lucky that I met many vegetarians through my college careers, many were happy to say why they chose it for themselves, many were not pushy. I think because I liked the people, I was eager to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through extended conversations, and especially because I made a close friend (Graduate Philosophy student) who was vegetarian, I warmed up to the arguments. I was lucky that my diet was primarily vegetables based (mom cooked soups, fried potatoes, etc) so it wasn’t hard to decrease my meat consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the longest time, and still, I think of vegetarianism as a continuum. This type of thinking makes it psychologically easier for people to eat less meat: they can feel like they are already doing something by eating less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it’s possible to be entirely vegan; one year that I was living alone I just refrained from buying animal products. But I think it’s better to be flexible (and not freak out over some butter in your restaurant dish) - this creates a more inviting picture for others to join. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important not to forget about the social component: you are able to do more by encouraging and inspiring others to change too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;When not trying to save the world, what do you do in your free time?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; I really enjoy reading and have read some amazing books in the past (I recommend some here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.yboris.com/reading.php&quot;&gt;http://www.yboris.com/reading.php&lt;/a&gt;). I like electronic music and listen often through the day (have been listening to trance/progressive house on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.di.fm/&quot;&gt;di.fm&lt;/a&gt; for over a decade). I enjoy spending time with friends, learning about and joking about trivial things. During the summer, hiking is one of my favorite activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m lucky to have met a partner for life, Yetzenia, now my fiancee. We live together and thus spend most of the time in each other’s company. I recently bought a used projector and with the help of a large white wall Yetzenia and I watch movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to the release-version of Oculus Rift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Last time we talked, you were involved in a massive cross-continental US road trip with your fiancee.  What’s that like?  What’s your favorite moment?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;B:&lt;/strong&gt; It’s hard to pick one. The 10,000-mile trip was wonderful and we both learned a lot about what we like and what we don’t. There were numerous beautiful moments, I’ll share one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most exhilarating moments for me was when I found a probably-five-story-high mountain of sand along the East Coast Highway in California (some miles north of LA); I walked up it for a long time, and then ran down. Yetzenia described that I looked like a gazelle. By the time I reached the bottom I was breathless, laughing, with tears running down my eyes from the wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Wow, that sounds really fun!  Well, thanks for taking the time to let me get to know you!  This was awesome!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cross-posted &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.effective-altruism.com/interview-with-boris-yakubchik/&quot;&gt;on the EA Blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/interview-with-boris-yakubchik/&quot;&gt;Interview with Boris Yakubchik&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on May 07, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Effective Altruism at TEDxDenisonU]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/effective-altruism-at-tedxdenisonu/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/effective-altruism-at-tedxdenisonu</id>
  <published>2014-04-22T04:54:27Z</published>
  <updated>2014-04-22T04:54:27Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, my university &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/tedx/events/9579&quot;&gt;had a TEDx event&lt;/a&gt;, and I was one of the people that got to give a talk:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/UKX_xzUGEcI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal of the talk was to present the idea that effectiveness in charity choice matters, with particular care to highlight the research of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givewell.org&quot;&gt;GiveWell&lt;/a&gt; and the work of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www3.imperial.ac.uk/schisto&quot;&gt;The Schistosomiasis Control Initiative&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my notes on how the talk went: &lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-went-well&quot;&gt;What Went Well&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video represents my current best guess on how to pitch effective altruism to a general audience.  I spent &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of time thinking about how to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I made it short.  Just seven minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I never mentioned the words “effective altruism”.  I think using and explaining the term tends to confuse more than inspire.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I mentioned only one topic (charity choice in giving), with one EA org (GiveWell), one example (SCI), and one call to action (look at GiveWell’s research).  This keeps it as simple as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I orginally thought of mentioning more things (like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givingwhatwecan.org&quot;&gt;Giving What We Can&lt;/a&gt;’s pledge), but chose not to, as this would make things more confusing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I tried to humanize the idea as much as possible.  I attempted to make my dilemma of charity choice relatable to the typical donor.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I specifically acknowledged that people give for non-EA reasons, and tried to frame my approach &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.givewell.org/2013/08/20/excited-altruism/&quot;&gt;as a source of excitement&lt;/a&gt;, not a moral obligation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I mentioned “two quarters” in addition to “fifty cents” to employ the &lt;a href=&quot;http://changingminds.org/techniques/general/sequential/disrupt_reframe.htm&quot;&gt;“disrupt and reframe” persuasion technique&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The talk was a really fun opportunity.  I broadened my horizons and met some cool people.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-could-have-gone-better&quot;&gt;What Could Have Gone Better&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The technical recording of the video isn’t that great.  There’s a weird black screen for the first couple of seconds, and the video lingers on my slides a little bit more than they should.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Despite rehersing for a &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; long time, I still felt nervous when presenting and messed up a tiny bit in two sections.  Overall, I think the performance was good given that I’m not the best at public speaking.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The title of the talk could have used some more thought to make it punchier, so that people would be more willing to click on it when they see it on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It probably would have been better to use images of Africans in my slides, but I did not have such pictures readily available and I was nervous about TEDx’s feelings of copyright.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The talk probably could have been even shorter.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I used the statistic that connects SCI with “fifty cents” and the Fred Hollows Foundation with “$40”.  I know both these statistics are potentially misleading.  I understand that SCI does not &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givewell.org/international/top-charities/schistosomiasis-control-initiative#Whatdoyougetforyourdollar&quot;&gt;save a life for fifty cents&lt;/a&gt; – their cost per treatment is actually now about $1 and cost per life saved higher than that.  I did choose SCI knowing full well that it would “sound better” than other high impact orgs, specifically because of the “fifty cents” statistic.  I couldn’t go down the “actually, things are more expensive than you expect, but still a good route” deal in a short tal but, in retrospect, it would have been more honest to stick to $1.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impact&quot;&gt;Impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The talk was given to an audience of about 200.  Since being posted online – and &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; I promoted it online – it’s received an additional 50 views.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Overall, my talk seems to have been very positively received.  I did not receive any negative comments or feel like anyone was distant from my talk, despite talking along side other non-profits that my message could have been seen as harmful towards.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Several people (as in ~6) specifically mentioned something positive to me, like saying that I had a really important message.  Another small handful (as in ~3) mentioned to me that they were definitely planning on checking out GiveWell.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcript&quot;&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 1: Blank]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day, I was walking with my friends.  It was cold out, so I was wearing my winter jacket.  As I was walking, I was fidgeting and checking my pockets.  And then came my surprise – in one of my pockets, I found a twenty dollar bill that I never knew I had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I showed it to my friends and we thought about what to do with it.  Maybe we should go out to lunch?  We weren’t sure.  Then one of my friends mentioned that, since I never knew I had the twenty, I never would miss it.   I should donate it to whoever needs it most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this was an excellent idea.  I wanted to donate my twenty to whoever needed it most.  But who was that?  I’ve heard of many different non-profit organizations and lots of different people in need.  Who needed my twenty dollar bill the most?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this was a strange notion – how am I supposed to compare charities?  Many people around me donate to “charity” …in general. They never would specify which charity or why. Giving was a personal choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends all had different ideas – the local food bank, other non-profits, even our own university.  We definitely have no shortage of charities competing for us.  We’re all bombarded by charity advertisements in our mailboxes and our emails.  Our universities have all asked us to make a Senior Gift.  We’ve all changed the channel when that sad commercial with the puppies comes around – you know which one I’m talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have much money as a college student, so I want to make my money count.  I want my $20 to go far.  Where can my money get the most impact?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My story started when I heard that giving should start at home.  I thought that was smart.  The needs here are important and I know organizations are helping.  But then I saw just how much further my money goes when spent in the developing world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 2: Choice]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, imagine I gave you this choice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Option A: Spend $40K and restore the eyesight of one blind person.
Option B: Spend $40K and restore the eyesight of one thousand blind people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully the choice is obvious – we’d all go for Option B.  You spend the same $40K in either scenario, but in Option B, 999 more people get their sight.  Option B is literally one thousand times better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…But this scenario – choosing between these two options – It’s all contrived, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 3: Blank]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not so fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In America, it’s often impossible to cure blindness.  However, we can go to Guide Dogs of America, a top non-profit that works on training guide dogs and providing them to blind people free of charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 4: Guide Dogs of America]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to them, the cost of training a guide dog and matching it with a blind person is $42,000.  Pay $42K and they train a dog, give it to a blind person, and that blind person can have a more normal life, able to get around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the developing world, people are often blind due to trachoma, which is a bacterial infection in the eye.  Curing trachoma is a simple procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 5: Guide Dogs + Fred Hollows]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All it takes to cure someone of blindness in the developing world is about $40 to the Fred Hollows Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the same cost as it takes to train a guide dog, I could cure 1000 people from blindness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this the case?  It’s not that the Guide Dogs of America is full of fraud.  They don’t funnel money to for-profit fundraisers or waste expenses on overhead.  It’s not even that the Fred Hollows Foundation is better run or more effective at doing their jobs than the Guide Dogs of America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, it’s  that the Fred Hollows Foundation is working in the developing world where money can go further.  The United States already eliminated trachoma in 1960, so it’s no longer a problem here.  Causes of blindness in the US are much harder to treat, because so many of the easy cases have already been treated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see the same difference when we look at poverty.  Let’s look at the amount of “extreme poverty”, or how many people live on an income of less than $2 a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, there is extreme poverty in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 6: Pie chart of US extreme poverty]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we take into account food stamps, subsidies, and tax credits, we find that 0.5% of Americans live in extreme poverty. This is bad, definitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 7: Pie Chart of US extreme poverty vs. Pie Chart of 3rd world extreme poverty]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the developing world, over 70% of people live in extreme poverty.  And that’s even after you take into account the fact that things are cheaper there.  Not to mention that people in the developing world don’t have access to things like food stamps, homeless shelters, or soup kitchens to stay afloat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 8: Simple Fact]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all led me to a simple fact.  Money just goes so much further to help people in the developing world.  I think of myself as a poor college student, but $20 barely gets me through my day.  It isn’t even enough to fill up a gas tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the developing world, things are different.  When you’re in extreme poverty, $20 is enough for two weeks.  In the developing world, having an additional $20 means you can buy food, invest in your home, pay school fees.   An additional $20 can be the difference that empowers you to get yourself out of extreme poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this simple fact was a powerful fact that really resonated with me.  Even with just $20, I could do so much for people in the developing world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 9: Blank]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I certainly don’t mean to trivialize the very serious problems in the US.  I wish I had enough money to cure blindness, poverty, and hunger both in the developing world and here in the United States.  But, unfortunately, I don’t.  Instead, my resources are limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 10: Choice]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, it comes down to a choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Option A or Option B?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 11: Blank]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are we supposed to do if we don’t know how to make our money go the furthest?  Certainly we can’t just work full-time investigating as many non-profits as we can to find the ones with the highest impact, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for us, there are already people working on just that.  Holden Karnofsky and Elie Hassenfeld used to be employed full-time in the hedge fund industry.  But then they decided they wanted to donate some of their salary.  To their surprise, they found it very difficult to get high-quality information about charities.  So they actually quit their jobs and created…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 12: GiveWell]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…GiveWell, a non-profit dedicated to finding outstanding giving opportunities and publishing their analysis to help donors decide where to give.  Now, anyone can go to www.givewell.org and read their in-depth research about how to make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 13: Blank]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GiveWell has been spending years finding the organizations that are the best of the best of the best.  The organizations they select are thoroughly vetted to make sure they’re what they do actually works.  GiveWell reviews research, does interviews, performs site visits, add deeply investigates each charity they evaluate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizations that GiveWell supports are proven, cost-effective, underfunded, and outstanding.  And you don’t have to take their word for it – they publish pages and pages of reviews for anyone to consult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s when I knew where I’d give my $20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 14: SCI]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GiveWell recommends a few top organizations.  My favorite is the Schitsosomiasis Control Initiative – a bit of a mouthful to say, I know.  It’s not a sexy name and it’s not a flashy charity.  Instead, it’s run by a bunch of academics at the Imperial College in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Schitsosomiasis Control Initiative – or SCI – focuses on doing one simple thing: treat children in the developing world for parasitic worm infections.  These are parasites that sit inside you and steal your nutrients as you eat them.  Instead of feeding yourself, you feed these worms.  SCI gets these worms out by giving children a simple tablet that costs only fifty cents to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two quarters, you can deworm a child.  Deworming causes improved health and nutrition.  Deworming also reduces the chance of dying early.  Moreover, when children are treated, they regain energy and are able to attend school, improving education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deworming has so many benefits, but there’s not enough people funding it yet.  Here’s a huge opportunity to make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 15: Option C]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So really, the choice is even better.  I’m really excited to be able to make such a large difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My heart motivated me to give in the first place.  But my head told me to think about it some, look at the research, and make an informed decision about where to give.  Because of this research, I just gave my $20 to SCI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just think – the $20 in my pocket I didn’t even know I had was enough to remove worms from 40 kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Slide 16: Blank]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know donations are a very personal and emotional manner.  Giving with your heart is great.  But I ask you to consider taking a similar journey as I did – find out where your money can go furthest and think more about your impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, passion and evidence can make a powerful combination when it comes to your donations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I urge you to visit www.givewell.org and consider combining your heard and your head.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/effective-altruism-at-tedxdenisonu/&quot;&gt;Effective Altruism at TEDxDenisonU&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on April 22, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Career Advice for Phyllis Schmidt: Choosing Between Masters, Software Engineering, and EA Direct Work]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/career-advice-for-phyllis-schmidt-choosing-between-masters-programming-and-direct-work/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/career-advice-for-phyllis-schmidt-choosing-between-masters-programming-and-direct-work</id>
  <published>2014-04-22T01:14:27Z</published>
  <updated>2014-04-22T01:14:27Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Recently, an effective altruist contacted me looking for career advice.  This EA had previously been working on a philosophy Ph.D., but recently decided to abandon the field due to insufficient stable job opportunities.  As abandoning the philosophy field is looked upon as very negative by those still in the field, this EA asked me to keep their identity anonymous.  Therefore, this person goes by the alias “Phyllis Schmidt”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phyllis is currently looking at a wide-variety of options for what to do next, looking to make an informed “best guess”, work on that career for a bit, and then re-evaluate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phyllis is currently considering (roughly ranked):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I-O psychologist&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Software engineer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Economist working on development (e.g., J-PAL)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Continue philosophy professor path &lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other options Phyllis is open to include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Working directly in an EA org&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Civil / public service&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Working in a foundation as a program officer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Management consulting&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Public health&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows are my notes to Phyllis on each of the options, followed by general advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-o-psychology-masters&quot;&gt;I-O Psychology Masters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phyllis has looked over &lt;a href=&quot;http://80000hours.org/blog/314-in-which-career-can-you-make-the-most-difference&quot;&gt;80k’s list of careers&lt;/a&gt;, but feels that pursuing a masters in industrial/organizational (I-O) psychology would be the best fit for her, given her talents and interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;potential-upside-of-i-o&quot;&gt;Potential Upside of I-O&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Phyllis, I-O has the potential to be a gateway toward high-earning jobs.  Psychology About &lt;a href=&quot;http://psychology.about.com/od/psychologycareerprofiles/p/iopsychcareers.htm&quot;&gt;pegs the salary&lt;/a&gt; as starting at $64K and rising to about $100K.  Phyllis plans to earn to give on this salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phyllis sees I-O as ripe for EA research potential.  I-O psych work aimed at the right sectors could fit in 80K’s category of “working inside international organisations, government or foundations to improve them”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, this career has not been well explored by EAs yet, and learning about the career could be a valuable contribution in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;potential-downsides-of-i-o&quot;&gt;Potential Downsides of I-O&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Need to take a year of pre-req classes to have a shot at getting into a masters program, which is not guaranteed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Masters program itself requires two years and tuition to complete, and an exiting job is not guaranteed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Options for non-PhDs appear limited, according to some Google searching and a conversation with an I-O psychology professor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;assessment-on-i-o&quot;&gt;Assessment on I-O&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have actually studied organizational psychology a fair amount, even getting a concentration in it.  However, I never considered going further in the career, and therefore I don’t know a whole lot about career opportunities, as I’ve never looked at the career much in depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like an interesting field with a mix of EA research potential and earning to give potential, though the research is not as good (in my opinion) as other psych topics (e.g., behavior change) and the earning to give is not as good as other opportunities.  I’d be concerned about trying to optimize for too much at once, however, as both EtG and research opportunities seem individually better elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the double-risk of failure is very daunting – you’re potentially putting a lot of time and money into something that could easily get you nowhere, with no easy way to find out in advance.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;software-engineering&quot;&gt;Software Engineering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;potential-upsides-to-software-engineering&quot;&gt;Potential Upsides to Software Engineering&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very high salaries for earning to give&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great work environments&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could lead to direct impact, depending on what you work on (e.g., productivity applications, AI, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;potential-downsides-to-software-engineering&quot;&gt;Potential Downsides to Software Engineering&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The field is pretty low risk, though you could spend a lot of time learning programming only for it to not work out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;assessment-on-software-engineering&quot;&gt;Assessment on Software Engineering&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This option has pretty high potential upside, so merits exploration.  Luckily, it should only take about 50 or so hours to determine provisionally if software engineering is a good fit.  I recommend Phyllis to complete Steps 1 and 2 in &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/learn-code/&quot;&gt;my programming guide&lt;/a&gt; and then decide if she wants to pursue this field further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;economics-masters&quot;&gt;Economics Masters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;potential-upsides-to-economics&quot;&gt;Potential Upsides to Economics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leads to a wide variety of favorable options after attaining a Ph.D. (high-paying finance jobs, government work, good EA research opportunities), but it’s unclear whether a masters would attain the same benefits.  Phyllis says there are programs like Master’s of Public Administration in International Development that could potentially lead to a job at the World Bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research while getting the degree could be useful to EA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;potential-downsides-to-economics&quot;&gt;Potential Downsides to Economics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long time to finish degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No guarantee to get into a program, and finishing the degree does not guarantee a good job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Might end up not matching Phyllis’s interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;overall-assessment-of-economics&quot;&gt;Overall Assessment of Economics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This route seems better to me than I-O or Philosophy, though I’d have to know more about Phyllis’s interests and economics background.  There still is a lot of potential risk here. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;continue-philosophy-phd&quot;&gt;Continue Philosophy Ph.D.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;potential-upsides-to-philosophy&quot;&gt;Potential Upsides to Philosophy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Potential influencing of students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already much of the way through a Ph.D. program (sunk cost)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;potential-downsides-to-philosophy&quot;&gt;Potential Downsides to Philosophy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Positions are very low pay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Positions are in geographic areas undesirable to Phyllis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phyllis is very burnt out in this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;assessment-of-philosophy&quot;&gt;Assessment of Philosophy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally tend not to recommend this path because I don’t think the impact is all that high, unless you get really lucky like Peter Singer, or you use it as a platform to do EA org work, like Toby Ord or Will Macaskill.  As Phyllis already seems to be looking very negatively upon this path, I don’t think it’s worth exploring further. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;direct-work-in-an-ea-org&quot;&gt;Direct Work in an EA Org&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of Phyllis’s previous work seems like it would make her well qualified to do good work in an EA org of some sort.  I recommend Phyllis look into this in a bit more depth.  Unfortunately, as Phyllis is American, the opportunities for stable employment in Oxford’s CEA are more limited, but not impossible.  I recommend Phyllis look into doing an internship with CEA and talk to people who work there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phyllis could also consider working for American EA organizations or EA-aligned non-profits.  American-based The Life You Can Save might be of particular interest to Phyllis.  Though I don’t believe they’re doing full hiring yet, I think Phyllis could potentially get an internship there to explore this opportunity further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;working-in-a-foundation&quot;&gt;Working in a Foundation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in a foundation has many potential benefits.  Unfortunately, &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/brief-notes-on-careers-in-foundations&quot;&gt;my analysis of foundation jobs&lt;/a&gt; shows that positions are very competitive and seem to require a lot of prior specialized education and experience.  If Phyllis wishes to work in a Foundation, I recommend pursuing a Ph.D. in economics first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-and-next-steps&quot;&gt;Conclusion and Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I generally err against recommending people take on Ph.D. programs without high certainty they’d enjoy and prosper in the field.  Unfortunately, this does not yet appear to be the case for Phyllis.  Moreover, earning to give opportunities seem higher for Phyllis in software engineering and research opportunities seem better for Phyllis in EA orgs.  Lastly, committing to a lot more school does not fit well with the “best guess and re-evaluate” plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I suggest Phyllis first look more heavily into software engineering and direct work in EA orgs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend to Phyllis the following next steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Complete Steps 1 and 2 in &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/learn-code/&quot;&gt;my programming guide&lt;/a&gt; and then decide if she wants to pursue this field further.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Talk to people in CEA, the Life You Can Save, and other EA orgs about what opportunities here might look like – including volunteer opportunities, internships, and full positions.  I’d be happy to make these connections.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;epilogue&quot;&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phyllis has agreed to look at my programming guide and is strongly considering applying to a programming bootcamp.  Phyllis has also been talking to US-based EA organization &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalcharityevaluators.org&quot;&gt;Animal Charity Evaluators&lt;/a&gt; about interning with them.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/career-advice-for-phyllis-schmidt-choosing-between-masters-programming-and-direct-work/&quot;&gt;Career Advice for Phyllis Schmidt: Choosing Between Masters, Software Engineering, and EA Direct Work&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on April 22, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sunday Links #26]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-26/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-26</id>
  <published>2014-04-20T07:31:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-04-20T07:31:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;What started out as some links and commentary on a discussion of Pigovian taxation &lt;a href=&quot;http://peterhurford.tumblr.com/post/83316812303/pigovian-taxation-and-confiscatory-taxation-boring&quot;&gt;ended up becoming an entire post on my Tumblr instead&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I did it again.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://peterhurford.tumblr.com/post/83319461315/how-much-does-money-matter-in-politics&quot;&gt;Now I analyze how much money matters in politics&lt;/a&gt;.  Answer: it’s complicated?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting way to think of ethics is as &lt;a href=&quot;http://lesswrong.com/lw/uz/protected_from_myself/&quot;&gt;protecting you from yourself&lt;/a&gt;: “But why not become an expert liar, if that’s what maximizes expected utility?  Why take the constrained path of truth, when things so much more important are at stake?  Because, when I look over my history, I find that my ethics have, above all, protected me from myself.  They weren’t inconveniences.  They were safety rails on cliffs I didn’t see.  I made fundamental mistakes, and my ethics didn’t halt that, but they played a critical role in my recovery.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of very lengthy discussions, here’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://raikoth.net/libertarian.html&quot;&gt;one on libertarianism&lt;/a&gt;, and why it’s sorta wrong sorta misguided sorta maybe?  On the other end of things (by the same author), we get a &lt;a href=&quot;http://slatestarcodex.com/2013/12/08/a-something-sort-of-like-left-libertarianism-ist-manifesto/&quot;&gt;left-libertarian manifesto&lt;/a&gt;.  Left-libertarianism sounds pretty good to me, quite in line with my discussion of Pigovian taxation earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting study looks at &lt;a href=&quot;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2421943&quot;&gt;how donors respond to evidence of effectiveness in advertisements of charities&lt;/a&gt;.  The paper hypothesizes that those who are altruistically-inclined respond positively to evidence, whereas those who are donating to seek a “warm glow” of personal happiness respond negatively to evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new Pew survey finds that Americans &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vox.com/2014/4/18/5626068/pew-survey-americans-terrified-new-technology&quot;&gt;don’t feel ready for a future of driverless cars, lab grown meat, and servant robots&lt;/a&gt;.  However, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://reason.com/archives/2010/12/27/from-yuck-to-yippee&quot;&gt;“From Yuck to Yippee”&lt;/a&gt; in Reason Magazine points out, people tend to be opposed to new potential technology right until they become actual, like in vitro fertilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-4-earning-to-give/&quot;&gt;wrote a summary of “earning to give”&lt;/a&gt;, or the idea of looking specifically for a high paying job in order to earn a lot of money, and then use your large disposable income to donate to charity.  Now, Pablo Stafforini has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stafforini.com/blog/writings-on-earning-to-give-an-annotated-bibliography/&quot;&gt;expanded that work into a larger annotated bibliography&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have heard that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2010/11/lies-damned-lies-and-medical-science/308269/&quot;&gt;90% of all medical research is flawed&lt;/a&gt;.  Turns out that &lt;a href=&quot;http://slatestarcodex.com/2013/02/17/90-of-all-claims-about-the-problems-with-medical-studies-are-wrong/&quot;&gt;this claim is flawed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-26/&quot;&gt;Sunday Links #26&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on April 20, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[So You Wanna Learn How to Code?  Going from Zero to Programmer Hero in One Guide, for Great Justice.]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/learn-code/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/learn-code</id>
  <published>2014-04-18T07:23:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-04-18T07:23:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/learn-code#changelog&quot;&gt;v1.6.20&lt;/a&gt; - Last Update: 22 Apr 2014 1:50p EDT - by Peter Hurford (&lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/learn-code#acknowledge&quot;&gt;with lots of help&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-introduction&quot;&gt;The Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you wanna learn how to code?  Whatever your motivation, computer programming and general computer know-how are good skills to have.  Programming knowledge can be potentially high value for careers or start-up opportunities, and with not too much time investment, you can figure out if programming is something you would enjoy and be good at.&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple paths to getting a programming job, learning programming, or whatever goal you may have.  &lt;strong&gt;There’s no “one true way”&lt;/strong&gt;, and there’s going to be a lot of conflicting advice on what is the “best” way to learn.  Honestly what is best is going to vary person by person, and based on your interests and goals.  I’ve designed a guide here based on my personal experience and had it tweaked based on feedback from other programmers.  This guide is heavy on web development and Ruby on Rails because those are the things I’ve had the most experience with, they seem like good places to start, and they seem quite employable.  That doesn’t mean that learning other languages is not a good idea.  This guide is designed with the mind to try and find your interests as soon as possible.  But it still might not be precisely right for you.  Your mileage may vary.  &lt;strong&gt;The best thing to do is just start, somewhere.&lt;/strong&gt;  See if this guide works for you, tweak if it doesn’t.  Let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, you might find out that programming is not a good fit for your skills and interests, and you have to be okay with that.  Keep in mind that true programming skill only comes from the long haul.  There is no real “learn X language in two hours” – even 100 hours of learning will only give you a beginner’s knowledge of one particular language.  “Programmer hero” status will only be achieved after many years of work.  So it’s important you really like it and stick with it, if you want to get anywhere.  Programming also seems to come best if you have multiple, uninterrupted, consecutive hours to devote to it – it appears much harder if it’s just 30 minutes here, 30 minutes there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, let me know (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/peterhurford&quot;&gt;Peter Hurford on Facebook&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#112;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&amp;#101;&amp;#114;&amp;#064;&amp;#112;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&amp;#101;&amp;#114;&amp;#104;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#102;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#100;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&quot;&gt;&amp;#112;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&amp;#101;&amp;#114;&amp;#064;&amp;#112;&amp;#101;&amp;#116;&amp;#101;&amp;#114;&amp;#104;&amp;#117;&amp;#114;&amp;#102;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#100;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&lt;/a&gt; by email) if you try this guide, so I can get feedback on how it goes for you.  Feel free to also reach out to me with comments on how to improve the guide – I’m still relatively new to programming myself and have not yet implemented all these steps personally!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-guide-pt-i----zero-to-beginner&quot;&gt;The Guide, Pt. I – Zero to Beginner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-one----codecademy&quot;&gt;Step One – Codecademy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know any programming at all, it would be a good idea to get a feel for it on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codecademy.com/dashboard&quot;&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt;.  Pick either &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codecademy.com/tracks/python&quot;&gt;the Python lesson&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codecademy.com/tracks/ruby&quot;&gt;Ruby lesson&lt;/a&gt;.  Spend about 5-10 hours on one of them (no need to finish it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a good test – Can you implement &lt;a href=&quot;http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?FizzBuzzTest&quot;&gt;FizzBuzz&lt;/a&gt; in either Python or Ruby?  Can you implement &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bubble_sort&quot;&gt;bubble sort&lt;/a&gt; in either of those languages?  If you answered no to the first question, definitely do this step.  If you answered yes to the first, but no to the second, consider doing this step.  If you answered yes to both, definitely skip this step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do this, see how you feel after the 5-10 hours are up.  How fun was it?  How much of a struggle was it?  How much time were you able to devote to it per week?  Is this something you can see yourself doing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think it’s necessary to complete the course, but feel free to finish it at this point if you wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-two----hartls-ruby-on-rails-tutorial&quot;&gt;Step Two – Hartl’s Ruby on Rails Tutorial&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve got good news and bad news for you.  The good news – real programming is actually a lot more fun and interesting than Codecademy.  The bad news – Codecademy is not real programming.  Codecademy is a good supplemental learning guide, but it isn’t comprehensive enough.  So we’re going to look to something a bit better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I’m going to recommend to you to complete &lt;a href=&quot;http://ruby.railstutorial.org/&quot;&gt;Michael Hartl’s Ruby on Rails tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.  Ruby on Rails is already a really popular and useful language right now, and is a very employable language to know if you want to go into the start-up / tech world.  The guide also provides useful introductions to many other important supporting technologies, like GitHub, RSpec, and Heroku.  You’ll also learn critical concepts like Model-View-Controller and test driven development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you complete this guide, make sure you never copy and paste the provided code – always retype it by hand.  You won’t really learn it if you just copy and paste.  Moreover, try all the provided exercises in each section.  That’s how you expand your knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My guess is that it should take you 30-60 hours to get through the tutorial.  Use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.beeminder.com/&quot;&gt;Beeminder&lt;/a&gt; or something if you feel like you’re not doing a good job at getting the hours in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optional-other-step-two----if-you-hated-hartls-tutorial&quot;&gt;Optional Other Step Two – If you hated Hartl’s Tutorial…&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally enjoyed Hartl’s tutorial a lot and think it’s a really great set-up to not just Ruby on Rails, but many other things (e.g., GitHub, getting a text editor, etc.).  But if you disliked it, don’t fear!  It doesn’t mean programming is right for you, it just means you’re different than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some other ways to learn the right amount of Ruby on Rails to progress to step three is to sign up for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeschool.com/&quot;&gt;Code School&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeschool.com/paths/ruby&quot;&gt;work through all the Ruby classes&lt;/a&gt;.  This costs money, but is worth it.  This is a decent method in my opinion and I believe is the preferred method of Ozzie Gooen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buck Shlegeris doesn’t like Hartl’s tutorial and prefers that people &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codecademy.com/tracks/ruby&quot;&gt;complete the Codecademy class for Ruby completely&lt;/a&gt; and then work through &lt;a href=&quot;http://testfirst.org/learn_ruby&quot;&gt;Test First’s Ruby Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.  I’ve not personally tried this, but Buck seems to have turned out pretty well, so it can’t be that bad.  Buck then says after the Test First tutorial to then also sign up for Code School and work through all the Ruby classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;yet-another-optional-other-step-two----consider-a-programming-bootcamp&quot;&gt;Yet Another Optional Other Step Two – Consider a Programming Bootcamp&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you feel like you enjoy programming and want to make a career about it, but haven’t been doing so well at self-teaching, you could consider going to a programming bootcamp.  These are more-than-full-time intense programs that teach you programming and help you with job placement.  Here, you set aside 10+ weeks, enroll in the site, learn from the program, and hopefully pop out with a job on the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never personally gone to a boot camp (and don’t plan to).   Keep in mind that a bootcamp is neither necessary nor sufficient to land a good programming job.  But for people with the time and inclination, it could be &lt;em&gt;a lot better&lt;/em&gt; than trying to go through this guide yourself.  If you’ve got the time, it’s definitely at least worth investigating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.appacademy.io/#p-home&quot;&gt;App Academy&lt;/a&gt; is widely considered to be the best program and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=site%3Alesswrong.com+app+academy&amp;amp;oq=site%3Alesswrong.com+app+academy&amp;amp;aqs=chrome..69i57j69i58.5575j0j7&amp;amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;amp;es_sm=91&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&quot;&gt;there’s been lots of discussion of it on LessWrong&lt;/a&gt;.  App Academy basically does Step 2-17 from this guide, but gives you support, formal teaching, and a good learning environment.  Buck Shlegeris is a TA at App Academy and is happy to be a contact if you’re interested in getting more information on applying and/or getting coached through the process.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://80000hours.org/blog/329-interview-with-buck-shlegeris-from-app-academy&quot;&gt;Here’s an interview with Buck about App Academy&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buck and Chris Hallquist (who went to App Academy) also say that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackreactor.com/&quot;&gt;Hack Reactor&lt;/a&gt; is the second-best program if you’re not able to get into App Academy (it is somewhat selective).  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.skilledup.com/learn/programming/the-ultimate-guide-to-coding-bootcamps-the-exhaustive-list/&quot;&gt;Here’s a full list of all available bootcamps, with details&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-three----a-personal-rails-project&quot;&gt;Step Three – A Personal Rails Project&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you should know enough to fail forward on a project of your own.  You’re off the bunny slopes and now it’s time to ski down the hill.  Personal projects are the most exciting and useful ways to learn code, and you now should know exactly enough (and not much more) to try your own Rails application.  So make something!  I made a &lt;a href=&quot;http://jobboard.im/&quot;&gt;Job Board&lt;/a&gt;, others made a &lt;a href=&quot;http://skillshare.im/&quot;&gt;Skillshare&lt;/a&gt;.  Hartl had you make a Twitter clone, but you could try to create a clone of another popular app like Reddit.  It doesn’t have to be useful, because the idea is just to learn code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be hard, but Googling around and &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/&quot;&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt; should get you farther than you think.  It also could be a really good idea to seek out a personal mentor or two, who can walk you through inevitable points where you get stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optional-step-four----another-rails-tutorial&quot;&gt;Optional Step Four – Another Rails Tutorial&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you feel like you’re struggling at this step, you could consider working through another Ruby/Rails tutorial to re-learn some of the stuff in a different context.  I like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.peterhurford.com/tilde/files/ruby-textbook.pdf&quot;&gt;Agile Web Development&lt;/a&gt; with Rails.  No need to do this if you feel like you’re going well, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-five----re-evaluate&quot;&gt;Step Five – Re-evaluate&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you are a certified beginner in Ruby on Rails.  Congratulations!  At this point, you could probably get an internship or Junior Developer position at a rapidly expanding tech company.  Not too bad for ~200 hours of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But more importantly – at this point, you should now be able to know if programming is for you.  Did you complete your personal project?  Was it fun?  (It should be fun.)  Was it hard?  (It should be hard.)  If you enjoyed yourself and found yourself able to put in a fair amount of time on it each week, then congratulations – programming might be for you!  But be honest with yourself, and don’t force it just because programming seems glamorous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optional-step-six----learn-python&quot;&gt;Optional Step Six – Learn Python&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier, in Step One, I had you look at either Python or Ruby.  Python is somewhat popular in the start-up world, though not nearly as popular as Ruby on Rails.  However, Python is really popular in the academic world.  It has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.numpy.org/&quot;&gt;good support for statistical programming&lt;/a&gt; and has a platform called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.djangoproject.com/&quot;&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; that acts similarly to Rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good language to know, but that being said, several of us don’t think it’s worth the time investment if you’re solely focused on getting into the start-up world and don’t have a particular use for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you’re interested, now would be a good time to pick it up.  If you’d like, work your way through &lt;a href=&quot;http://learnpythonthehardway.org/&quot;&gt;“Learn Python the Hard Way”&lt;/a&gt;, skimming a bit as necessary.  Also, give a look through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.greenteapress.com/thinkpython/thinkpython.pdf&quot;&gt;“Think Python”&lt;/a&gt;, though you’ve probably learned much of it already from completing “Learn Python the Hard Way”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-guide-pt-ii----skiing-the-blue-squares&quot;&gt;The Guide, pt. II – Skiing the Blue Squares&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-seven----an-interlude-for-htmlcss&quot;&gt;Step Seven – An Interlude for HTML/CSS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think now is a good time to switch gears.  Ruby on Rails is a language that does back-end, or helps you get information on the server to the user.  But we also want to give you some experience in front-end, or making that information usable and well presented.  Hartl’s tutorial gave you some intro to this and you probably worked on some of this for your personal project, but now it’s time to take it to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skip this if you already know HTML and CSS pretty well.  Neither is particularly hard, but both are completely essential for front-end development.  That is, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patrickbrinichlanglois.com/&quot;&gt;could you re-create a simple personal website like this&lt;/a&gt; by hand, with minimal looking up of things online?  Feel free to try.  Even if you’ve never done HTML and CSS before, you might have picked up enough to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can’t (don’t worry!), read through Shay Howe’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://learn.shayhowe.com/html-css/terminology-syntax-intro&quot;&gt;Beginner HTML/CSS Guide&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://learn.shayhowe.com/advanced-html-css/performance-organization&quot;&gt;Advanced HTML/CSS Guide&lt;/a&gt; (though “advanced” is a bit of a misnomer here).  After you’re done, try to re-create the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-eight----and-now-javascript&quot;&gt;Step Eight – And Now, JavaScript&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll start with the undisputed base language for front-end development – JavaScript.  Let’s start by working our way through the entire &lt;a href=&quot;http://eloquentjavascript.net/index.html&quot;&gt;“Eloquent JavaScript”&lt;/a&gt; textbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-nine----javascript-design-patterns&quot;&gt;Step Nine – JavaScript Design Patterns&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design patterns are reusable solutions to common programming problems.  They’re really good to know.  Let’s learn some JavaScript design patterns.  Work your way through &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/addyosmani/essential-js-design-patterns&quot;&gt;“JavaScript Design Patterns”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-ten----go-advanced-on-javascript&quot;&gt;Step Ten – Go Advanced on JavaScript&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it’s time to get a little more advanced and learn more about what JavaScript can do.  Work your way through &lt;a href=&quot;http://ejohn.org/apps/learn/&quot;&gt;“Learn Advanced JavaScript”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-eleven----connect-back-to-back-end-work-with-nodejs&quot;&gt;Step Eleven – Connect back to Back-End work with Node.js&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work your way through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nodebeginner.org/&quot;&gt;“The Node Beginner Book”&lt;/a&gt;.  If you want to learn more about Node.js, consider also working through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.manning.com/cantelon/&quot;&gt;“Node.js in Action”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-twelve----get-intermediate-on-ruby&quot;&gt;Step Twelve – Get Intermediate on Ruby&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now seem to know more JavaScript than Ruby, so it would be good to catch up here.  Let’s read through Peter Cooper’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.peterhurford.com/tilde/files/beginningruby.pdf&quot;&gt;“Beginning Ruby”&lt;/a&gt; and then David Black’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://techedu.cu.cc/Programming/ruby/The%20Well-Grounded%20Rubyist/The%20Well-Grounded%20Rubyist.pdf&quot;&gt;“The Well Grounded Rubyist”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-thirteen----build-a-more-complex-application&quot;&gt;Step Thirteen – Build a More Complex Application&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You now know a lot of Rails and JavaScript, and it’s time to bring it all together.  Make something cool.  Much cooler than your last app.  Show off both your front-end and back-end skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-guide-pt-iii----aiming-for-a-job&quot;&gt;The Guide, pt. III – Aiming for a Job?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-fourteen----re-evaluate-again&quot;&gt;Step Fourteen – Re-evaluate, Again&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier, I mentioned that you knew enough to consider applying to a programming job.  At this point, this is even more the case.  You now know the beginnings to both a front-end and back-end framework and can build sites on your own.  If you were interested in applying to a job, consider looking into that now.  Think now about if that’s right for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-fifteen----get-an-intro-to-algorithms&quot;&gt;Step Fifteen – Get an Intro to Algorithms&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, it could be a good idea to learn some more about algorithms – this is a good idea even if you’re not aiming for a job.  First, reaTry to sign-up for and work through the Coursera class on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/algs4partI&quot;&gt;Algorithms I&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/algs4partII&quot;&gt;Algorithms II&lt;/a&gt;.  It’s best if you can do them while they’re live, but not necessary.  You can also supplement this work by skimming through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.beust.com/algorithms.pdf&quot;&gt;“Algorithms” textbook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optional-step-sixteen----read-cracking-the-coding-interview&quot;&gt;Optional Step Sixteen – Read “Cracking the Coding Interview”&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re aiming for a Senior Developer job at a tech company, it would be really helpful to tie this algorithm knowledge to how you’ll need to know it – in the interview.  Read through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.valleytalk.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/10/CrackCode.pdf&quot;&gt;“Cracking the Coding Interview”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optional-step-seventeen----do-other-basic-job-stuff&quot;&gt;Optional Step Seventeen – Do Other Basic Job Stuff&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a GitHub account if you haven’t already and put some projects there.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a nice portfolio website for your work (like &lt;a href=&quot;http://chrishallquist.com/&quot;&gt;Chris’s&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.peterhurford.com&quot;&gt;mine&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Read through &lt;a href=&quot;http://lesswrong.com/lw/hd1/maximizing_your_donations_via_a_job/&quot;&gt;Alexei’s account of getting a software job&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a list of companies you want to apply to.  Ask people to add to your list.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Seek out people to give you advice on how to apply and perhaps give you internal referrals in a company (very valuable to have).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Familiarize yourself with basic job etiquette like thanking interviewers by e-mail afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do some google searches for interview questions beyond what you read about in “Cracking the Coding Interview” – some questions are basic trivia unrelated to coding, such as questions about hexadecimal or how the internet works.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider creating an &lt;a href=&quot;http://ankisrs.net/&quot;&gt;Anki deck&lt;/a&gt; of information to know for interviews.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optional-step-eighteen----complete-some-problem-sets&quot;&gt;Optional Step Eighteen – Complete some Problem Sets&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides building your portfolio with projects, another good idea would be to complete some problem sets.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://projecteuler.net/&quot;&gt;Project Euler&lt;/a&gt; asks you to solve math problems in any programming language, which is a good test of creativity and math skills.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://codeforces.com/problemset&quot;&gt;CodeForces Problem Sets&lt;/a&gt; are similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://exercism.io/&quot;&gt;Exercism&lt;/a&gt; is also good – they’re not nearly as math-oriented, but instead offer Ruby and Python (and other) challenges where you try to make code work a given test suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://codility.com/&quot;&gt;Codility challenges&lt;/a&gt; also more closely approximate what you might encounter in an interview, with the two-star problems being about the difficulty you should expect, according to Chris Hallquist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems good to try to get a breadth of challenge from all four, though I’d stick more to Exercism and Codility if you’re looking for a position in web development / software engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, continuing with this guide couldn’t hurt.  The stuff after this guide appears to give much less marginal returns for entry-level jobs, but they’re still important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-guide-pt-iv----black-diamond-javascript-and-ruby&quot;&gt;The Guide, pt. IV – Black Diamond JavaScript and Ruby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-nineteen----test-driven-development-for-javascript-with-mocha&quot;&gt;Step Nineteen – Test Driven Development for JavaScript with Mocha&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not looking for a job, or just want to take your skills to the next level, there’s still more guide.  I now suggest you learn some good tests for JavaScript and jQuery.  Mocha is a nice platform for testing your front-end code.  Work your way through &lt;a href=&quot;http://visionmedia.github.io/mocha/&quot;&gt;the Mocha tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-twenty----learn-backbonejs-and-angularjs&quot;&gt;Step Twenty – Learn Backbone.js and Angular.js&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work your way through &lt;a href=&quot;http://addyosmani.github.io/backbone-fundamentals/&quot;&gt;“Developing Backbone.js Applications”&lt;/a&gt;.  You could then consider also learning Angular.js by working through &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.angularjs.org/tutorial&quot;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://egghead.io/&quot;&gt;these videos&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-twenty-one----learn-more-sql&quot;&gt;Step Twenty-one – Learn more SQL&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rails handles most of the SQL for you, and you’ve probably already learned some SQL through other tutorials.  But at this point it could be nice to just get it done.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://sqlzoo.net/wiki/Main_Page&quot;&gt;SQLZoo&lt;/a&gt; is a nice interactive tutorial here.  Let’s complete it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optional-step-twenty-two----watch-railscasts&quot;&gt;Optional Step Twenty-two – Watch RailsCasts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://railscasts.com/&quot;&gt;RailsCasts&lt;/a&gt; cost money, but they’re an excellent resource for learning how to do particular things in Rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optional-step-twenty-three----skim-around-with-bentobox&quot;&gt;Optional Step Twenty-three – Skim around with BentoBox&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bentobox.io/&quot;&gt;BentoBox&lt;/a&gt; is another site with a lot of resources for learning programming.  While less structured than this guide, it offers more depth, and provides resources for learning many things that are not contained in this guide.  Maybe you could start learning PHP or Java, maybe you might take up building mobile apps, or who knows?  BentoBox provides some resources to help with all of that as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optional-step-twenty-four----learn-some-data-science&quot;&gt;Optional Step Twenty-four – Learn Some Data Science&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to work in front-end and back-end, another popular programming career is data science.  This is a bit of enthusiasm on my part, but statistical programming can be pretty fun and open up a whole new world about what programming can do.  And statistics is, next to programming, one of the great skills to know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know stats or want a refresher, work through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udacity.com/course/st101&quot;&gt;Udacity’s Intro to Stats class&lt;/a&gt;.  Then work through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/dataanalysis&quot;&gt;Coursera’s Data Analysis class&lt;/a&gt; – it’s much better if you can catch it while live, because it’s a pretty dynamic class.  After that, work through &lt;a href=&quot;http://adv-r.had.co.nz/&quot;&gt;“Advanced R Programming”&lt;/a&gt; and then try your hand at some &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kaggle.com/competitions&quot;&gt;Kaggle tutorials and competitions&lt;/a&gt;.  This &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kaggle.com/c/titanic-gettingStarted&quot;&gt;tutorial on the Titanic is good&lt;/a&gt;, and has &lt;a href=&quot;http://trevorstephens.com/post/72920580937/titanic-getting-started-with-r-part-2-the&quot;&gt;a companion guide that teaches more R&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’re here, if you want to get really serious into Data Science, I’m pretty sure you’ll have to learn Hadoop and/or MapReduce.  But you should have done the hard part already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optional-step-twenty-five----celebrate&quot;&gt;Optional Step Twenty-five – Celebrate!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should now know enough about programming that you’re off on your own.  If you’ve found a good mentor, they can tell you what to do next.  Or maybe now you can land a programming job and learn programming in a real-world context.  Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-acknowledgements-a-nameacknowledgenbspa&quot;&gt;The Acknowledgements &lt;a name=&quot;acknowledge&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This advice is based on my personal experience, plus advice given to me (in rough descending order of magnitude) by Richard Batty, Chris Hallquist, Robert Krzyanowski, Ozzie Gooen, and Buck Shlegeris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-changelog-a-namechangelognbspa&quot;&gt;The Changelog &lt;a name=&quot;changelog&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.0.0 - Initial launch&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.0.1 - Added more info to intro&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.0.2 - Added version tracker&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.1.2 - Added alternatives to Hartl’s tutorial&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.1.3 - Added my contact information&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.1.4 - Added call for action for feedback&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.1.5 - Added Changelog&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.1.6 - Added more info about “multiple routes” to intro&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.2.6 - Added info on programming bootcamps&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.2.7 - Added more info on Python&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.3.7 - Added an explicit step for HTML/CSS&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.3.8 - Added more info on when one can apply to an internship / Junior position&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.4.8 - Added another re-evaluate period&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.4.9 - Added Codility to the list of problem sets&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.4.10 - Added info on Hack Reactor&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.4.11 - Added FizzBuzz test for the first step&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.5.11 - Added more info on getting a job&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.5.12 - Reorganized some of the steps&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.6.12 - Added a step for SQL&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.6.13 - Minor fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.6.14 - Added more information on App Academy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.6.15 - Tweaked intro.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.6.16 - Typo fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.6.17 - Added BentoBox.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.6.18 - Added reference to list of Bootcamps.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.6.19 - Added link to interview with Buck.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;v1.6.20 - Fixed some broken links.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/learn-code/&quot;&gt;So You Wanna Learn How to Code?  Going from Zero to Programmer Hero in One Guide, for Great Justice.&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on April 18, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sunday Links #25]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-25/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-25</id>
  <published>2014-04-07T01:41:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-04-07T01:41:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was recently &lt;a href=&quot;http://careyryan.com/peter-hurford/&quot;&gt;interviewed by Ryan Carey&lt;/a&gt; about the effective altruist movement, movement building, .impact, and work on the far-future.  Yay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exercising regularly is really important for living longer, staying smarter and healthier, being less depressed, being more attractive, being more respected, and being higher energy.  But what should we do?  Recently, I’ve been enjoying the guides put together by &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/16gJJeE1HdUl2BHCL19qAs-P4GrcnFTmibNdW5X3COLU/edit&quot;&gt;Rob Wiblin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://lesswrong.com/lw/juc/optimal_exercise/&quot;&gt;Romeo Stevens&lt;/a&gt;.  Personally, I like to run twice a week and do &lt;a href=&quot;http://stronglifts.com/&quot;&gt;the Stronglifts weightlifting program&lt;/a&gt; three times a week.&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://squid314.livejournal.com/326120.html&quot;&gt;Psychiatric hospitals are less “Cukoo’s Nest” and more “Catch-22”&lt;/a&gt;: “When it gets cold or rainy, the hospital fills up with homeless people. Word has spread on the streets that if you go to the emergency room and tell the nurse that evil spirits are telling you to kill everyone, you will get a nice bed and three warm meals a day (the hospital meals, in contrast to all conventional wisdom, are really good). It can be hard to turn these people away, since bloodthirsty lawyers are circling the hospital waiting for you to make a Type II error (“So, Dr. Alexander, you’re saying this homeless man walked right into your hospital and explicitly told you evil spirits were telling him to kill everyone, and you refused to even admit him to the hospital long enough to evaluate him more carefully? And this happened just before his shooting rampage at City Hall?”). Besides, many of the people with genuine mental illnesses are homeless, so you can’t conclude much either way until you’ve done a proper evaluation which means letting them in for a few days at least.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mrmoneymustache.com/2013/05/20/financial-reportin-sucks/&quot;&gt;Why we should fire the entire “financial advice” industry&lt;/a&gt;.  The real life-changing idea is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mrmoneymustache.com/2013/02/22/getting-rich-from-zero-to-hero-in-one-blog-post/&quot;&gt;early retirement&lt;/a&gt; (or extreme frugality) – you can live a really great life on $10K a year or so, and thus, with stocks, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mrmoneymustache.com/2012/05/29/how-much-do-i-need-for-retirement/&quot;&gt;you can retire on $250K&lt;/a&gt;.  With an after-tax income of $50K, you’ll have what you need to retire after just six years of work (savings rate of 80%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to know what economic reforms you should be fighting for?  Rolling Stone clocks &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/news/five-economic-reforms-millennials-should-be-fighting-for-20140103&quot;&gt;five economic reforms millenials should be fighting for&lt;/a&gt;: the job guarantee, universal basic income, the land-value tax, a US sovereign wealth fund, and public banking.  Not to be outdone, Washington Post takes the exact same five economic reforms and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2014/01/07/five-conservative-reforms-millennials-should-be-fighting-for/&quot;&gt;frames them for conservatives&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olof Johansson-Stenman presents research that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stafforini.com/txt/Johansson-Stenman%20-%20Are%20most%20people%20consequentialists.pdf&quot;&gt;typical ethical intuitions can be in line with consequentialism&lt;/a&gt;.  Elsewhere, utilitarianism is linked with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022103110000302&quot;&gt;higher testosterone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3234136/&quot;&gt;activity in the ventromedial prefrontal cortex&lt;/a&gt;.  Though I’m taking all these findings with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/139817/jacob-n-shapiro/the-business-habits-of-highly-effective-terrorists&quot;&gt;The Business Habits of Highly Effective Terrorists&lt;/a&gt;.  Strangly applicable to other businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-25/&quot;&gt;Sunday Links #25&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on April 07, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Favorite Productivity Apps]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/my-favorite-productivity-apps/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/my-favorite-productivity-apps</id>
  <published>2014-04-05T02:20:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-04-05T02:20:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I use a lot of different apps on the internet to save time for myself.  I thought I’d categorize the apps I personally use.  I’ve tried to sort them from most to least relevant for who I imagine the typical person who reads this article will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getpocket.com/&quot;&gt;Pocket&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Allows you to save online articles to read later, even offline and across devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://workflowy.com/&quot;&gt;Workflowy&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; A collapsable outline for taking notes and thinking about ideas.  Can be used to store and organize anything, from recepies to to-do lists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://adblockplus.org/en/chrome&quot;&gt;AdBlock Plus&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Remove ads from the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.one-tab.com/&quot;&gt;One Tab&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; “Whenever you find yourself with too many tabs, click the OneTab icon to convert all of your tabs into a list. When you need to access the tabs again, you can either restore them individually or all at once.”&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;** &lt;a href=&quot;http://justgetflux.com/&quot;&gt;Flux&lt;/a&gt;:** “It makes the color of your computer’s display adapt to the time of day, warm at night and like sunlight during the day.  It’s even possible that you’re staying up too late because of your computer. You could use f.lux because it makes you sleep better, or you could just use it just because it makes your computer look better.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ifttt.com&quot;&gt;ITTT&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; IFTTT (If This, Then That) is probably the most powerful app on the internet in terms of what it can do.  Basically, it’s an app that lets you set up custom, automatic responses to certain events.  For example, I use IFTTT to automatically post these blog posts to Facebook and Twitter by using recipes like “If new post in RSS, then post to Twitter”.  IFTTT also helps automatically populate the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/smartgiving&quot;&gt;r/smartgiving subreddit&lt;/a&gt; that I help out with.  And it can be used for dozens of other things, like giving you a warning about rain on your phone, automatically backing up files, having a change in your Facebook profile picture automatically change all your other profile pictures across the internet, automatically log things on Google Calendar, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thetimezoneconverter.com/&quot;&gt;The Time Zone Converter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; I frequently correspond with people in Europe, Australia, Chicago, and California, so I need something to keep my time zones straight.  I’ve tried six different apps for this, and this one is my favorite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wolframalpha.com/&quot;&gt;Wolfram Alpha&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; An impressive online calculator (“knowledge engine”) that can handle an impressive amount of input, from solving calculus to figuring out probabilities of various Poker hands, with a lot inbetween.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cronometer.com/&quot;&gt;Cronometer&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Cronometer tracks your nutrition (macronutrients and micronutrients) and makes sure you’re on track.  Good way to spot check a diet and see if you’re missing something important.  A lot of foods are already built-in, so you very infrequently need to enter in things for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.beeminder.com/&quot;&gt;Beeminder&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Automatic commitment contracts to keep you on track in your goals, whatever they may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.online-stopwatch.com/full-screen-interval-timer/?c=vxv55r3380&quot;&gt;This custom 25min-5min timer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, that I use for implementing &lt;a href=&quot;http://pomodorotechnique.com/&quot;&gt;the Pomodoro technique&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://politicalwire.com/&quot;&gt;Political Wire&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; So not really an app, technically, but still a time-saver.  It’s a really efficient way of learning about what is happening now in the world of US politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rumkin.com/tools/cipher/manipulate.php&quot;&gt;Text Manipulator&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; “Need to change something from lowercase to uppercase? Count the letters, numbers, and punctuation? Remove spaces or add spaces at every X characters? This can help.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.video2mp3.net/&quot;&gt;YouTube to MP3 Converter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Does exactly what it says it does.  I’ve tried four different ones of these and this one is my favorite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rainymood.com/&quot;&gt;RainyMood&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Rain sounds in your browser.  What could be better?  Doesn’t really save you time &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;, but could make you more productive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bufferapp.com&quot;&gt;Buffer&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes I come up with fun stuff I want to say on Facebook and Twitter, but it’s two in the morning and would be a bad time to post it.  Buffer lets me schedule these things for later, which lets me space out the things I would share.  This is probably like using a fire hose to put out a candle in terms of functionality, but it’s free and works well.  Good thing to use if you really like Facebook and Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://beta.gtimereport.com/&quot;&gt;GTime Report&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Exports your Google calendar into an Excel spreadsheet.  Great for doing &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/personal-review-for-december-2013-february-2014/#title&quot;&gt;some time analysis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gaisma.com/en/&quot;&gt;Giasma&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; I like to know when sunset and sunrise are – mostly because of idle curiosity, but sometimes for figuring out when to go to bed or wake up.  Giasma logs sunsets and sunrises for the entire world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://domchristie.github.io/to-markdown/&quot;&gt;HTML to Markdown&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Painlessly converts HTML script into the Markdown format.  Does not do the reverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tools.pingdom.com/fpt/&quot;&gt;Pingdom&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Tests page load speed and does server pings and traceroutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://magic.bluebones.net/proxies/&quot;&gt;MTG Proxy Generator&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Quickly make proxies for “Magic: The Gathering” cards.  Probably not relevant for that many people, but this app has personally saved me hours of time.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/my-favorite-productivity-apps/&quot;&gt;My Favorite Productivity Apps&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on April 05, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brief Notes on Careers in Foundations]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/brief-notes-on-careers-in-foundations/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/brief-notes-on-careers-in-foundations</id>
  <published>2014-04-02T16:03:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-04-02T16:03:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently been looking at some potential careers that may be of interests to effective altruists.  While I’m certainly pretty happy to look into web development, I think another strong career option that is not very frequently mentioned is working in a foundation.  I’d love to look into this more deeply, but I thought it would be good to first offer some preliminary thoughts on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I’ve only spent four hours on this, including the time it took to write this post.  As such, it’s very likely I’ve missed important considerations.  If there is enough interest, I – or someone else – could look into this more deeply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foundation work seems potentially high impact for EAs because salaries are high and matching programs are generous.  For exmaple, a senior program officer for the Gates Foundation can potentially donate $209K a year while still keeping $30K/year for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Foundation work also offers major influencing opportunities that many other EA careers lack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;However, jobs at foundations appear very competitive and hard to get.  A survey of the top ten foundations by asset size shows that program associates require around 5+ years of prior relevant experience, and program officers require around 8+ years of prior relevant experience plus a Masters degree or Ph.D.  Though there may be other routes in, such as non-program positions (e.g., accountant) or internships.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Overall, working for a foundation is potentially a high-impact career, though not as high impact as I may have first guessed.  Because of the high amount of prep work needed, it seems like a foundation job would not be as potentially high impact as working in computer programming or finance – which offer similarly high salaries with less prep time – or law – which requires similar prep time, but offers higher salaries.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It seems like foundation work would be a good option for people who already have the relevant qualifications (Masters degree, multiple years of experience) to try for, or for someone to try and get in via an alternate route, like an internship.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-might-a-foundation-career-be-promising&quot;&gt;Why Might a Foundation Career Be Promising?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Salaries are good for earning to give.&lt;/strong&gt;  A program officer seems to make around $122K a year, though can be as high as $197K being a Senior Program Officer in the Bill &amp;amp; Melinda Gates Foundation.  More “entry level” positions, such as program assistants, make around $49K a year.  (Source: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.glassdoor.com/&quot;&gt;Glassdoor&lt;/a&gt;, averaged for the top ten foundations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Donation matching programs are very generous.&lt;/strong&gt;  As Joey Savoie wrote for 80K, &lt;a href=&quot;http://80000hours.org/blog/168-how-to-double-your-donations-with-no-extra-effort&quot;&gt;this sweetens the deal even more&lt;/a&gt; – a matching program is like an instant raise for being an EA!  The best programs are offered by the Ford Foundation and the Bill &amp;amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, which both offer a 3:1 match up to $30K.  This means that if you earn $179K as a Gates Foundation Senior Program Officer and donate everything you earn above $30K, you can donate $209K a year to any 501(c)3 organization!  And the Ford and Gates Foundations are not alone – the Moore Foundation offers a 2:1 match up to $30K, the RWJF matches 1:1 up to $50K, and the Hewlett Foundation matches 1:1 up to $20K.  Though, of course, make sure your foundation has a matching program and confirm what it does before assuming it as a part of your plan!  (Source: &lt;a href=&quot;http://doublethedonation.com/&quot;&gt;Double the Donation&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A chance to influence foundation money.&lt;/strong&gt; The top ten foundations each work with billions of dollars.  By being a program officer, you essentially have a full time job influencing the foundation to donate to what you think is more effective.  Though, of course, you tend to be very limited in precisely what you want to donate to (can’t move everything to CEA or MIRI, for example) and are not the sole decider on this.  But could be an important path to even more impact!  For example, the Gates Foundation has an annual budget of $3.4B – with 1194 staff members, naïve division gives $2.8M to each staff member.  Though, of course, not all staff have equal influence.  Moreover, it would be good to take care to select a foundation based on how receptive they would be to EA principles before joining.  For example, global poverty focused Gates Foundation would be a better choice than the developed-world-library-and-art-preservation focused Getty Trust.  (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arnoldfoundation.org/&quot;&gt;The Laura and John Arnold Foundation&lt;/a&gt; is rumored to be particularly EA-friendly.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A chance to influence other foundation workers.&lt;/strong&gt; People working at the foundation are usually doing so because they’re altruisticly inclined.  You also know they have good salaries and generous donation matching programs to boot!  Maybe you could influence not just your own donations, but those of several other people in the foundation.  Again, foundation match is an important aspect here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good way to potentially learn relevant things to inform EA.&lt;/strong&gt;  Your foundation work may happen upon a charity not currently known to EAs that ends up being really effective, or may shine light on important research.  Also, the regular operations and management of foundations might be good examples to be applied at EA orgs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good way to keep up altruistic motivation.&lt;/strong&gt; Donation matching makes donating even more salient and you’re potentially surrounded by other altruistic people.  Certainly makes it easier to be altruistic yourself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-might-a-foundation-career-not-be-promising&quot;&gt;Why Might a Foundation Career Not Be Promising?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Restrictions on donation matching.&lt;/strong&gt; If most of your impact is from donation matching, you run the risk of the org you want to donate to being not a registered 501(c)3 US charity.  Additionally, you run the risk of the foundation you’re working for modifying their donation matching program unfavorably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The jobs are really hard to get.&lt;/strong&gt; See the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-would-one-work-for-a-foundation&quot;&gt;How Would One Work for a Foundation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if one was interested in working in a foundation, how would one break in?  To answer this, I decided to look at the careers page of &lt;a href=&quot;http://foundationcenter.org/findfunders/topfunders/top100assets.html&quot;&gt;the top ten foundations by asset size&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://careers.gatesfoundation.org/&quot;&gt;Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; The Gates Foundation has 52 current positions open – more than any other foundation.  Entry level jobs require 5+ years of relevant experience in the domain, and look very favorably on a Masters degree, with more education and experience required for higher positions.  Careers here appear to be highly competitive.  It seems nearly impossible for one to work here as a first job.  It seems best to instead come from another foundation, non-profit, government agency, or consulting job first – after getting a Masters degree.  Another potential route in is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gatesfoundation.org/Jobs/Internship-Program-FAQ&quot;&gt;an internship&lt;/a&gt;, but access is restricted only students in certain (top) business schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fordfoundation.org/careers/current-openings/&quot;&gt;Ford Foundation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Positions at the Ford Foundation are very limited in quantity and require a high amount of domain-specific knowledge for the job.  Like the Gates Foundation, though maybe even more so, one be thinking of this as a second, third, or fourth job rather than a first one.  One potential route in is to take a non-Program Officer position, like an Auditor or Technician, though these roles also seem competitive and require certifications and prior experience.  The Ford Foundation also offers internships, though only for students in New York, New Jersey, and Connecticut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jobs-getty.icims.com/jobs/search?ss=1&amp;amp;searchLocation=&amp;amp;searchCategory=&amp;amp;hashed=0&quot;&gt;The Getty Trust&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; The Getty Trust has 34 open positions.  Senior program officer positions seem just as hard as other foundations, but junior program officers seem easier to get, only requiring three years of prior experience and a Masters degree.  However, a lot of Getty Trust positions are limited to people with knowledge of art history and library science, which may not be studied frequently by EAs.  Additionally, some non-Program Officer positions seem easier as well – for example, the Software Engineer position only requires three years of prior experience.  Moreover, The Getty Trust has numerous assistant positions open, such as data entry, which can be had without even a college degree (though salaries are much lower here – around $25K/year).  The Getty Trust also has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.getty.edu/foundation/initiatives/current/gradinterns/index.html&quot;&gt;internships available&lt;/a&gt; for graduate students studying something relevant to Getty Trust activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rwjf.org/en/about-rwjf/job-opportunities.html&quot;&gt;Robert Wood Johnson Foundation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;  RWJF only has four positions open, and program officer positions are in line with other foundations (7+ years experience, Masters degree required, PhD preferred).  However, RWJF is also advertising for a Research Asisstant position, which only requires 1-2 years of experience in Health outside of a Bachelors Degree, which seems promising.  No internships publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wkkf.org/employment&quot;&gt;W. K. Kellog Foundation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Only advertising for a handful of positions.  Requirements on experience seem lower, but not by much.  No internships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hewlett.org/about-us/careers&quot;&gt;William and Flora Hewlett Foundation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;  They’re looking for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hewlett.org/node/13669&quot;&gt;a Program Associate for something they call an “Effective Philanthropy” group&lt;/a&gt;!  And it doesn’t have any onerous stated requirements beyond a college degree.  Cool!  Overall, the Hewlett Foundation has at least less &lt;em&gt;stated&lt;/em&gt; requirements than the other foundations, but it still seems competitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lillyendowment.org/&quot;&gt;Lilly Endowment&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; They do not appear to be advertising for any open positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.packard.org/about-the-foundation/jobs/&quot;&gt;David and Lucille Packard Foundation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Program officer positions are looking for 5+ years of prior experience and a Masters degree; program assistant positions looking for 3+ years of prior experience and a Bachelor’s degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://newton.newtonsoftware.com/career/CareerHome.action?clientId=8ad8dbd13c0b6151013c1c85827e42fd&quot;&gt;Macarthur Foundation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Appear to be only hiring for internships right now, though they appear to be available to any American college student who will not be graduating this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moore.org/about/careers&quot;&gt;Gordon and Betty Moore Foundation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Program Officer requires a Ph.D. with 5 more years of experience.  Program Associate requires a Masters and 2 more years of experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like working for a foundation is potentially a high-impact career, though not as high impact as I may have first guessed.  Most notably, the high need for qualifiications and high competition for the job make it an unreliable choice for someone to “aim” for.  For example, it seems way to risky to get a masters degree and acquire 5+ years of relevant experience in a field, all for the hope of landing a Program Officer position, and then not get the position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, because of the high amount of prep work needed, it seems like a foundation job would not be as potentially high impact as working in computer programming or finance – which offer similarly high salaries with less prep time – or law – which offers a similar risk, but higher salaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, it seems like a good option for people who already have the relevant qualifications (Masters degree, multiple years of experience) to try for, or for someone to try and get in via an alternate route, like an internship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine the best next step is to find a few people currently working in foundations and ask them more about career opportunities there.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/brief-notes-on-careers-in-foundations/&quot;&gt;Brief Notes on Careers in Foundations&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on April 02, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A .impact Review]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/a-dot-impact-review/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/a-dot-impact-review</id>
  <published>2014-03-31T05:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-03-31T05:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;.impact is a group of people who want to volunteer on really useful projects. This means, however, we need some idea of whether or not our projects are actually useful. Thus, the purpose of this essay is to analyze whether or not our projects have been useful, whether putting more time and money into .impact is worth the cost, where .impact has stumbled, and what our plans for the future are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;.impact has worked on a total of 25 projects, 8 of which have been launched (Skillshare, Improving EA Presence on Wikipedia, EA Interview Series, Utilitarian Essays Redesign, CEA Homepage Redesign, Giving What We Can Redesign, and the EA Reddit).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Right now, we think the core benefits of .impact can be categorized as working on (a) building the EA community, (b) building EA infrastructure, (c) learning about volunteering, (d) giving people skills and credibility, and (e) encouraging an ethos of trying things.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our case is not very rigorous.  A lot of our evidence is anecdotal, and most of our impact  lies in our yet-to-be-realized potential as an organization.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;.impact has encountered setbacks.  We’ve found the supply of volunteering to be more limited than expected.   We’ve also found volunteer software projects to be more difficult than originally assumed, with it taking much more time than expected to make much progress on projects.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’ve also found it difficult to predict how useful our projects would be.  So far .impact has not progressed as much as we would like in systematic needs analysis, metric measurement, or project prioritization.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The original goal of some of our members to learn programming through doing programming projects has been more difficult to realize.  Aligning high-impact development with education has proven challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Our costs to date have been ~$50 and ~860 person hours (valued at $34.4K).  However, much of .impact work is in the free time, and opportunity costs seem to be lower than one would initially expect.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Overall, we’re quite confidant that we justify our costs and we look forward to seeing what happens in the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;see-the-rest-of-the-review&quot;&gt;See the rest of the review…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dotimpact.im/2014/03/31/what-has-dot-impact-done-so-far/&quot;&gt;…on the .impact blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/a-dot-impact-review/&quot;&gt;A .impact Review&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on March 31, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fyfe-Hurford Debate: My Round One]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/fyfe-hurford-debate-peter-round-one/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/fyfe-hurford-debate-peter-round-one</id>
  <published>2014-03-28T05:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-03-28T05:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Over at Felicifia, Alonzo Fyfe, blogger at &lt;a href=&quot;http://atheistethicist.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;Atheist Ethicist&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://secularite.com/real-world-ethics-alonzo-fyfe/&quot;&gt;The Secularite&lt;/a&gt;, and I &lt;a href=&quot;http://felicifia.org/viewtopic.php?f=7&amp;amp;t=1024&quot;&gt;had a debate&lt;/a&gt; on “Which is a better theory of utilitarianism – Alonzo Fyfe’s desirism or Peter Hurford’s two-level utilitarianism?”.  I wanted to reprint that debate here.  Here’s the second entry (of eight).  This entry was written by me.  This is a continuiation of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/fyfe-hurford-debate-alonzo-round-one&quot;&gt;previous entry written by Alonzo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to first spend some of my precious word count mentioning how much of an honor it is to be engaging with Alonzo Fyfe on this important issue.  In many ways I owe Alonzo a lot for where I am today.  In 2011, I was a huge fan of desirism.  I learned many aspects of moral philosophy from reading Fyfe and became interested in ethics due to following Alonzo’s journey to figure out the right thing.  Perhaps ironically the first place I learned about the “two level utilitarianism” was from Fyfe himself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this debate, I offer “two-level utilitarianism” as a better view of utilitarianism.  However, I agree with Alonzo that this is more of a friendly discussion than a debate.  I must admit it might be hard for Alonzo to give up desirism after spending so much of his life defending it, just as it would be hard for me to give up utilitarianism after having a blog called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;“The Everyday Utilitarian”&lt;/a&gt;.  But I rest assured that we are both beholden to the truth more than our particular brands of utilitarianism and believe we can be trusted to update our beliefs in the face of new arguments.&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-two-level-utilitarianism&quot;&gt;What is “Two-Level Utilitarianism”?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1981, R. M Hare wrote a book called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Moral-Thinking-Levels-Methods-Point/dp/0198246609&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moral Thinking: It’s Levels, Method, and Point&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in which he defends preference utilitarianism in theory, but argues that the human condition requires two levels of utilitarianism in practice – an intuitive level of rule utilitarianism and a critical level of act utilitarianism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hare notes that throughout much of our life we operate at an intuitive level where we don’t have the time to think through a situation and we have to act on habit and internalized thinking.  At this intuitive level, we implement rule utilitarianism, where we internalize a set of rules and follow them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Hare argued that, as often as is possible, we should re-evaluate these rules for ourselves and engage in full and deliberate reflection.  At this critical level we implement act utilitarianism and perhaps resolve a particularly difficult moral problem and figure out ways to update our moral rules so that they better guide us to maximize utility in our intuitive moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-makes-one-utilitarianism-better-than-another&quot;&gt;What Makes One Utilitarianism Better Than Another?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this debate, we seek to find the “best” version of utilitarianism.  But, in doing so, we need some method to make judgments about what makes a theory of utilitarianism better than another.  Alonzo did not overtly outline any specific criteria, so I thought I would suggest one: if the best utilitarian act is the act that maximizes utility and the best utilitarian rule is the rule that maximizes utility, I suggest that the best version of utilitarianism is the version that maximizes utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This principle of meta-utilitarianism makes sense – utilitarianism should not be self-defeating when followed, so we therefore should adopt whatever theory actually accomplishes utilitarian ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-the-case-for-two-level-utilitarianism&quot;&gt;What is the Case for Two-Level Utilitarianism?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I call “stereotypical act utilitarianism the naïve strawman theory of utilitarianism that we should, in practice, be straightforward utilitarians exactly as described in the textbook – from the moment we wake up to the moment we go to sleep, we should analyze every option available to us and choose only that which maximizes utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many theorists have pointed out that stereotypical act utilitarianism doesn’t work because of problems like how difficult it is to calculate utility for everything and how we will often suffer from imperfect information.  Faced with these methodological and motivational problems to utilitarianism, I suggest we abandon stereotypical act utilitarianism in practice while keeping it in theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.princeton.edu/~kahneman/docs/attention_and_effort/Attention_lo_quality.pdf&quot;&gt;Kahneman (1973)&lt;/a&gt; points out that we only have a finite amount of energy to allocate to each decision in our life.  Research in psychology has put forth “dual processing theory” where we have a “System I” style of thought that is quick, reflexive, and intuitive and a “System II” style of thought that is slow, reflective, and analytical.  This dual processing theory fits two-level utilitarianism perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we’re realistic, we have to be comfortable with the fact that many of our decisions will be intuitive.  Indeed, making an intuitive snap decision without fully calculating out all the options will actually be the act utilitarian thing to do when we account for the fact that these calculations drain our energy and take time away from our ability to focus on other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that doesn’t mean we should stop there.  In fact, I think that while we shouldn’t strive to be act utilitarians at all times, the vast majority of people would become better at producing utility if they were more reflective and self-aware, not less.  When we have time to reflect, we can deliberately engage in “System II” processes (or operate at the critical level, as Hare calls it) and reflect upon our rules to sharpen them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This divide provides us with the need for a two-level utilitarianism in order to fit it pragmatically.  It’s also this divide between situations that prevents rule utilitarianism from collapsing into act utilitarianism, which was a worry of Alonzo’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-makes-rules-better-than-desires&quot;&gt;What Makes Rules Better Than Desires?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desirism asks us to desire that which we have many and strong reasons to desire.  From a moral standpoint, this means adopting desires that help satisfy the desires of others.  However, it is far harder to alter your desires on a fundamental level than it is to maintain a desire to follow the best rules (out of a desire to be moral, perhaps) and then alter the rules you possess.  There’s also a &lt;a href=&quot;http://commonsenseatheism.com/?p=11191&quot;&gt;concern that desires do not exist&lt;/a&gt;, while rules certainly do exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, desirism does not elaborate on the role of reflection like two-level utilitarianism does.  What process are we engaging in when we decide what desires to adopt?  How do we change our own desires?  In answering these two questions, how is desirism different from rule utilitarianism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-utility--dont-know-but-not-intrinsic-value&quot;&gt;What is Utility?  Don’t Know, But Not Intrinsic Value.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One area where our moral systems seem to diverge is in attitudes toward utility.  Alonzo is fond of how desirism need only operate on desires and does not need any “intrinsic value” or “value-laden term”.  I agree with Alonzo in his critique of brain-state theories of value.  Personally, I have not yet found a satisfactory reduction of utility that is sufficiently rigorous and resolves moral dilemmas in a way that satisfies me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, for now, the utilitarian choices are pretty clear pragmatically without a robust theory of utility.  What’s important for the sake of this debate is that, like desirism, my version of two-level utilitarianism also does not rely on any “intrinsic value” or spooky stuff in order to work.  Instead, utility matters because people (and other beings capable of experience) matter, and these lives matter to me simply because I have a desire to make their lives better.  I consider myself to be a moral anti-realist and have therefore constructed an anti-realist version of utilitarianism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-ought-we-do-in-an-exotic-situation&quot;&gt;What Ought We Do in an Exotic Situation?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another possible divergence is the “10000 Sadist Problem”.  Because this situation is so bizarre and unlike situations we encounter in everyday life, it’s likely that our normal rules and intuitions might fail to maximize utility.  Therefore, we should go to the critical level if time allows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I’d like to mention that the better utilitarian theory is the one that maximizes utility, not the one that gives the response to hypothetical scenarios that satisfies people’s intuitions.  This is what Luke Muelhauser calls &lt;a href=&quot;http://commonsenseatheism.com/?p=523&quot;&gt;the wrong test for moral theories&lt;/a&gt;, precisely because we don’t have a reason to expect the correct moral answer to always be the intuitive one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, I don’t think two-level utilitarianism would have you give up the kid to the 10000 sadists.  Many people think that utilitarianism suggests that the needs of the many outweigh the needs of the few.  This isn’t precisely right, because utilitarianism also takes the strength of the need into account.  In this case, the need of the kid to avoid being tortured is intensely strong.  So strong, I’d suspect, that it still outweighs the satisfaction that the 10000 sadists get.  Generally, pain hurts a lot more than pleasure satisfies both in intensity and duration, and therefore can be expected to dominate in this calculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;just-how-utilitarian-is-desirism-anyway&quot;&gt;Just How Utilitarian is Desirism, Anyway?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does Desirism Actually Maximize?&lt;/em&gt;
Alonzo suggests that desirism resolves the 10000 Sadists by suggesting we look at the desire to torture and ask if we need that desire.  Because we don’t possess reasons for a desire to torture, we can safely discard it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, who possesses the reasons for having or discarding desires?  The 10000 sadists themselves certainly have many reasons to keep their desire to torture – they get satisfaction from doing so.  The “10000 Sadists Problem” attacks utilitarianism’s maximization process, arguing (naïvely) that the utility gained by the 10000 sadists outweighs the utility lost by the tortured kid.  In order to discard the desire to torture, desirism must go against this grain of maximization and do something else.  I’m not sure what this process is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why Does Desirism Not Count Future People?&lt;/em&gt;
Secondly, from a theoretical standpoint, I worry that desirism does not take desires into account that do not yet exist.  Perhaps Alonzo feels this is a feature and not a bug, and certainly “person-affecting” theories of utilitarianism are held among many theorists.  However, most utilitarian theories believe that future people matter just as much as present people, and we shouldn’t discriminate against them in our analysis just because they don’t yet exist.  I don’t know what Alonzo’s reasoning is for making this distinction into a morally relevant one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, while I don’t believe matching intuitions is important, this desire to help future people does match our intuitions – think of the desire to curb global warming or tackle large social challenges that will only benefit people several generations from now.  The very desire to leave a better Earth for future generations presupposes that future generations matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does Desirism Hear The Strongest Needs?&lt;/em&gt;
Lastly, from a pragmatic standpoint, I worry that desirism does not do a good enough job identifying which desires are the most numerous and most strong.  Right now, I believe one of the most pressing needs is extreme poverty in the developing world.  Two-level utilitarianism explicitly states we should evaluate needs objectively, and therefore brings extreme poverty to our attention.  However, the desires of these people to be free from extreme poverty don’t speak very loudly and don’t weigh much on the minds of us Americans.  When we Americans think of desires we have strong reasons to support, we think of those desires that speak to us loudly and end up supporting many first-world causes.  I think this is a utilitarian mistake and would hope the utilitarian theory we adopt guides people easily to this understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I offer two-level utilitarianism as the utilitarian theory that is better suited to maximize utility when implemented in practice.  I’ve argued in favor of two-level utilitarianism because it (a) fits with findings in psychology that we have two processing systems and limited attention to allocate to every event in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This theory is more practical than desirism because (b) rules are more malleable than desires, (c) the role of reflection in desirism is less clear, (d) desires may not exist, and (e) two-level utilitarianism makes it clearer impartial attitudes matter when considering what problems ought to be prioritized morally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I’ve argued that desirism falls short of utilitarianism because it (f) has a strange attitude toward maximization and (g) does not take the welfare of future people into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I’ve answered Alonzo’s problem with utility by agreeing with him and arguing that two-level utilitarianism also only relies on entities that exist.  I also answered Alonzo’s 10000 Sadist Challenge by arguing that it is the wrong test for a moral theory.  And I answered Alonzo’s concern that rule utilitarianism collapses into act utilitarianism by showing the impossibility of being act utilitarian all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/fyfe-hurford-debate-peter-round-one/&quot;&gt;Fyfe-Hurford Debate: My Round One&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on March 28, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Personal Review for December 2013 - February 2014]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/personal-review-for-december-2013-february-2014/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/personal-review-for-december-2013-february-2014</id>
  <published>2014-03-26T05:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-03-26T05:00:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Follow up to &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/six-month-review-ii-june-november-2013/&quot;&gt;“Six Month Review II: June-November 2013”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, I’ve publicly published &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/a-year-of-mostly-new-years-resolutions/&quot;&gt;monthly reviews&lt;/a&gt; where I’ve reviewed progress on habits and published &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/six-month-review-ii-june-november-2013/&quot;&gt;six-month reviews&lt;/a&gt; where I’ve gone in-depth on personal life strategy.  While I still aim to review myself &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/how-i-am-productive/&quot;&gt;on a daily, weekly, and monthly basis&lt;/a&gt;, I am no longer going to publish these.  Instead, I’ve recently found that the monthly review is too quick to have meaningful things to say, while the six-month review is too slow.  Therefore, I’ve consolidated into a three-month review.  Here’s my personal review for the months of December, January, and February.  I’ve been delayed in getting this out due to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/behold-the-new-site&quot;&gt;site redesign&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-my-path-to-impact&quot;&gt;What Is My Path to Impact?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it useful to start this review by stating my plans, and then seeing how well I did against these plans.  Broadly, I still self-identify as an &lt;a href=&quot;http://lesswrong.com/lw/hx4/four_focus_areas_of_effective_altruism/&quot;&gt;effective altruist&lt;/a&gt;, which means I want to do my best to make the world a better place.  But easier said than done!  How do I aim to do that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;my-plan-broadly&quot;&gt;My Plan, Broadly&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/where-im-giving-and-why/&quot;&gt;“Where I’m Giving and Why”&lt;/a&gt;, I write that there is “a huge priority to learn more about opportunities for doing good” and therefore “I’ve decided to spend my money and time trying to figure out how to learn more in reliable ways” (see also &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/why-im-skeptical-about-unproven-causes-and-you-should-be-too/&quot;&gt;me on unproven causes&lt;/a&gt;, my &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/where-ive-changed-my-mind-on-my-approach-to-speculative-causes/&quot;&gt;follow-up to that post&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.effective-altruism.com/paul-christiano-on-cause-prioritization-2/&quot;&gt;Paul Christiano on cause prioritization&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;long-term-the-three-year-plan&quot;&gt;Long-Term (The Three Year Plan)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote in &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/my-case-study-i-mostly-finished-choosing-between-careers/&quot;&gt;“My Case Study: I (Mostly) Finished Choosing Between Careers”&lt;/a&gt; that I’m currently aiming to be in “full-time employment for 40-60 hours a week, but then spending significant portion of my ‘free time’ volunteering and doing EA side projects”.  I will be starting work doing web development and statistics for a Chicago-based start-up on the 30th of June.  By splitting my time this way, I hope to learn a lot more about my earning potential, my ability to do EA projects, and how the value of these two things might compare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, over the next three years I’d like to take an opportunity to try work in several different spheres – &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/pitching-effective-altruism/&quot;&gt;marketing/outreach&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/could-ea-community-building-be-an-easy-and-underfunded-win/&quot;&gt;community building&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/for-impact-the-future-matters-more/&quot;&gt;cause prioritization research&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalcharityevaluators.org/research/organizations/organization-evaluation-template/&quot;&gt;strategic research&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/career-advice-for-jacy-choosing-between-ph-d-programs/&quot;&gt;coaching&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dotimpact.im&quot;&gt;project management&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-4-earning-to-give/&quot;&gt;earning to give&lt;/a&gt; – and see where I am best suited to the EA movement.  Over the next three years (12 review cycles), I hope to have a strong preliminary determination about where I am most useful.  After that, I will either (1) continue to do the mixed model of earning to give and EA work, (2) focus solely on earning to give, or (3) &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mrmoneymustache.com/2013/02/22/getting-rich-from-zero-to-hero-in-one-blog-post/&quot;&gt;retire early&lt;/a&gt; and focus solely on EA work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-term-the-three-month-plan&quot;&gt;Short-Term (The Three Month Plan)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next three months are March, April, and May.  After May is done, there will only be one month until I start my job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main focus of my short-term plan will then be to focus on pre-professional prep.  This means learning a lot more statistics and programming.  I’d like to learn more back-end (Ruby on Rails, mainly), front-end (JavaScript, mainly), and Big Data stuff (R, Hadoop, MapReduce).  This should then put me in a strong position for my upcoming job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d also like to support my longer-term plan.  I’d like to bring much greater organization to my projects in each sphere, for greater transparency and tracking.  Then, I’d like to try a little in each.  I’d like to arrange it so rather than trying everything at once, I do more things one-at-a-time to maintain higher focus (though I also think I thrive on having high variety in my tasks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-this-plan-and-not-others&quot;&gt;Why This Plan, and Not Others?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan seems best in a fairly obvious way.  Building programming strength seems like a great way to &lt;a href=&quot;http://80000hours.org/blog/238-how-to-assess-the-impact-of-a-career&quot;&gt;build career capital&lt;/a&gt; and increase my potential earnings a lot, and furthermore opens up other opportunities for volunteering or maybe even &lt;a href=&quot;http://80000hours.org/blog/256-should-more-altruists-consider-entrepreneurship&quot;&gt;creating a technology start-up&lt;/a&gt;.  Learning seems best from an EA point-of-view, since it will increase my impact over many years to come if I find better things to do, which I expect I will, and I might be able to influence others as well.  Such learning, considered as “cause prioritization”, is also listed by 80,000 Hours as &lt;a href=&quot;http://80000hours.org/blog/300-which-cause-is-most-effective--300&quot;&gt;the best cause&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-i-spend-my-time&quot;&gt;How Did I Spend My Time?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;winter-break&quot;&gt;Winter Break&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 20 December to 19 January, I was at home, between semesters in college.  I had no concrete schedule and could largely do whatever I wanted.  I chose to break up my time as follows.  I intentionally focused a lot on socializing (seeing friends).  My other focus was on programming – getting through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ruby.railstutorial.org&quot;&gt;Ruby on Rails Tutorial&lt;/a&gt; – and on settting up &lt;a href=&quot;http://dotimpact.im&quot;&gt;.impact&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that other includes things like showering, hygeine, prioritizing my work, travelling, packing/unpacking, visiting the dentist, getting a haircut, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Activity&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;Hours Per Week&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;Per Day&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;% of Day&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;% of Awake Day&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sleep&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;55.7&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;8.0&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;33%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Friends&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;40.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;5.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;24%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;36%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;24.1&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3.4&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;14%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;21%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Break&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;14.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.1&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;9%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;13%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Programming&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;11.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.7&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;.im&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;11.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.7&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Write&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;5.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;5%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Exercise&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;4.4&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;4%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;ACE&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.2&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Senior Research&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.9&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jan&quot;&gt;20-31 Jan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 20th of January, I returned for my final semester at college.  I added up Beta Theta Pi (my fraternity), Homework / Class, Denison Community Association (DCA), and Denison Venture Philanthropy (DVP) as timeblocks because they’re my school activities.  Time was broken up as follows.  I was heavily focused on Beta because I was in charge of coordinating recruitment for the Spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition for working for ACE (0.58hrs/wk), projects included writing a play (2.03hrs/wk), volunteering for 80K (0.28hrs/wk), and doing EA-related research into career choice (0.58hrs/wk) and CFAR (1.02hrs/wk).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Activity&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;Hours Per Week&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;Per Day&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;% of Day&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;% of Awake Day&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sleep&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;53.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;7.7&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;32%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;18.5&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.7&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Friends&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;18.4&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;12%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;HW/Class&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;13.7&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;8%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;9%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Break&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;11.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.7&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;8%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Programming&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;6.9&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;4%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;6%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;ACE / Projects&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;4.5&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Beta&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;22.9&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;14%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;14%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Senior Research&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.2&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;.im&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;5.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;DCA&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Write&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.4&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Exercise&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.2&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;DVP&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.04&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;february&quot;&gt;February&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I no longer had to work as much for Beta, I focused more on Programming and Senior Research.  I also began working on putting together a TEDx talk about strategic philanthropy.  Classes also ramped up a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Activity&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;Hours Per Week&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;Per Day&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;% of Day&lt;/th&gt; &lt;th&gt;% of Awake Day&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sleep&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;53.4&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;7.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;32%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Other&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;21.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3.0&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;13%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;13%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;HW/Class&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;18.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.6&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;12%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Friends&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;15.0&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.1&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;9%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;.im&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;13.1&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.9&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;8%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;9%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Break&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;12.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;8%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Programming&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;10.1&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.4&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;6%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;9%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;TEDx&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;6.7&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.0&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;4%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;4%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Beta&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;6.4&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.9&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;4%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;4%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Senior Research&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;4.9&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.7&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Exercise&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.5&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;DCA&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.4&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;DVP&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;2.2&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Write&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.8&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;0.3&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1%&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;is-my-time-properly-aligned-with-my-goals&quot;&gt;Is my time properly aligned with my goals?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My time is my most valuable resource, so I want to make sure that it’s working for me as best as is possible.  Broadly speaking, I do think the way I spend my time is properly aligned with my goals, with the exception of winter break.  On winter break, I probably spent a bit too much time sleeping and with friends – though this was probably acceptable given the circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like it was probably a mistake to do senior research – while I do get some returns (social status, research experience, contact with professionals, potential publication), the returns do not seem worth the time investment, compared to other opportunities that I have.  However, at this point with a final draft already written and only one more month to go, it seems like it would be a mistake to drop it, even after taking into account the &lt;a href=&quot;http://youarenotsosmart.com/2011/03/25/the-sunk-cost-fallacy/&quot;&gt;sunk cost fallacy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I seem to be doing the right things and my output also seems high.  I might be open to criticism from not having the right balance between my projects, but I don’t see any clear room for improvement.  I might also be open to critism from trying to do too much at once, but I don’t see any activities I can easily drop before graduation in May.  At this point in the middle of my final semester, I should just stay the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-i-accomplish&quot;&gt;What Did I Accomplish?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;thinking-through-complex-issues&quot;&gt;Thinking Through Complex Issues&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“What should I do when I graduate?”&lt;/strong&gt; I end up largely settling this question for myself in &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/my-case-study-i-mostly-finished-choosing-between-careers/&quot;&gt;“My Case Study: I (Mostly) Finished Choosing Between Careers”&lt;/a&gt;, where I settle on web development and announce that I will be starting a web development job this summer.  I also &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/second-interview-with-jon-behar-on-giving-games/&quot;&gt;interviewed Jon Behar a second time&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/career-advice-for-jacy-choosing-between-ph-d-programs/&quot;&gt;give career advice to Jacy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No progress on other questions.&lt;/strong&gt; Despite asking “What normative framework should I choose?”, “What would someone acting out utilitarianism in their everyday life look like?”, “How, if at all, can utilitarianism be presented as a robust moral theory?”, “What causes should a utilitarian focus on?”, “How, if at all, should I change my lifestyle?” and making goals to work further on these questions by the next review, I have not published progress on any of these questions, though I did think about the issues personally and have &lt;a href=&quot;http://felicifia.org/viewtopic.php?f=7&amp;amp;t=1024&quot;&gt;outlined many of my thoughts in an online debate with Alonzo Fyfe&lt;/a&gt;.  Publishing concrete progress on these questions will be a goal to accomplish by the next review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;blogging-generally&quot;&gt;Blogging, Generally&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t write much during this three month period.  I decided that writing wasn’t as high impact at the moment as the other opportunities I was faced with (e.g., putting together the TEDx presentation, putting togehter .impact, and working on career development by learning programming).  I now intend to try to keep up writing again because I think that there are some high-value things for me to think through that would also be of interest to other people.  But I need to keep in mind that it’s still generally a better idea for me to focus on building up more important skills, like programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve aimed to begin a daily writing habit, and I hope to sustain that in small doses every day to keep my writing going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;animal-charity-evaluators&quot;&gt;Animal Charity Evaluators&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my previous list of goals, I had “volunteer for like-minded communities”.  Over the past three months, this was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalcharityevaluators.org/&quot;&gt;Animal Charity Evaluators&lt;/a&gt; (ACE), where I assisted in putting together their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animalcharityevaluators.org/research/organizations/organization-evaluation-template/&quot;&gt;“Organization Evaluation Template”&lt;/a&gt;.  ACE is now beginning to make a round of research and recommendations based on this template.  I think this was a high-value project to influence the direction of ACE and I’m excited to see how it turns out.  Right now, it doesn’t seem like I will be doing additional volunteering for them, though I’m still open to the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;impact&quot;&gt;.impact&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to volunteering with ACE, over the past three months, I spent a significant amoutn of my time helping start &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dotimpact.im/&quot;&gt;.impact&lt;/a&gt;, “a distributed volunteer force of effective altruists working on really useful projects”.  This involved work on four projects – &lt;a href=&quot;https://impact.hackpad.com/.meta-e1HVjGcw27B&quot;&gt;.meta&lt;/a&gt;, or work on organizing .impact as a whole; &lt;a href=&quot;https://impact.hackpad.com/Studying-Vegetarian-Advocacy-m11aW51ENVW&quot;&gt;a study of the impact of Facebook ads on vegetarians&lt;/a&gt;; creating &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/smartgiving&quot;&gt;r/smartgiving&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://impact.hackpad.com/EA-Reddit-CgvrZdkwXWV&quot;&gt;Reddit for EA&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://impact.hackpad.com/Job-Board-G2ZocnkVTsc&quot;&gt;the Job Board&lt;/a&gt;, which has mostly just been an outlet to learn programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think there has been a decent amount of value from these projects and .impact as a whole, with a lot of potential and learning value yet to be realized.  A more detailed review of .impact is forthcoming shortly.  I intend to continue work in .impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tedx&quot;&gt;TEDx&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another opportunity I had was to participate in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/tedx/events/9579&quot;&gt;TEDxDenisonU&lt;/a&gt;, which was a TEDx talk featuring 12 different speeches from Denison students, Denison faculty, and the wider Denison community.  This seemed like a great opportunity to share a message of strategic philanthropy, and I took it, talking about GiveWell and SCI.  I also took the opportunity to practice honing my pitch.  I hope to share more on this when the YouTube version of the talk is publicly available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;learning-programming&quot;&gt;Learning Programming&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve learned a significant amount of programming over the past three months, having put in a combined 110 hours into learning.  I’ve completed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/course/dataanalysis&quot;&gt;Coursera “Data Analysis” class&lt;/a&gt; which brought me up to intermediate level knowledge of the statistical language R (~45 hours to complete) and I completed &lt;a href=&quot;http://ruby.railstutorial.org/ruby-on-rails-tutorial-book&quot;&gt;Michael Hartl’s Ruby on Rails tutorial&lt;/a&gt; (~40 hours).  Both of these tutorials are highly recommended.  I also worked on the Job Board to further learn Ruby on Rails; enrolled in a Computer Science course at Denison focused on Python, C++, and data structures / algorithms; and am working through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kaggle.com&quot;&gt;Kaggle&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://adv-r.had.co.nz&quot;&gt;“Advanced R”&lt;/a&gt; to learn more R techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, I hope to soon start working through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Agile-Development-Rails-Pragmatic-Programmers/dp/1934356549&quot;&gt;“Agile Web Development with Rails”&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://javascriptissexy.com/how-to-learn-javascript-properly/&quot;&gt;“Javascript is Sexy”&lt;/a&gt; to learn more Ruby/Rails and JavaScript respectively.  I hope to write up more on my experiences learning programming, as well as collaborate with some other programmers to create a guide to help other people learn programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;finding-and-talking-to-cool-people&quot;&gt;Finding and Talking to Cool People&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still continue to be very excited about my level of connecting with the people in my life.  I’ve worked a bit more on acheiving some work-life balance with regard to this.  I’ve now &lt;a href=&quot;http://dotimpact.im/meetings.html&quot;&gt;Skyped with many people for .impact&lt;/a&gt; and personally, as well as correspondend with people via other mediums.  I’ve also worked harder to connect with other friends in my life, including my Beta brothers and my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;making-denison-university-a-better-place&quot;&gt;Making Denison University a Better Place&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://everydayutilitarian.com/essays/six-month-review-ii-june-november-2013/&quot;&gt;My previous review&lt;/a&gt; made a point of trying to scale down my involvement in on-campus activities.  Ultimately, over the past three months I have succeeded in scaling down my involvement, but not as much or as quickly as I might like.  I intend to continue to try to scale down and transition my involvement in all Denison acitvities as I prepare to graduate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;eating-and-exercise&quot;&gt;Eating and Exercise&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My exercise has not been conformed to the “three days lifting, two days running” as often as I’d like.   I need to renew my focus here, especially with regard to running, which has been hard to motivate myself to do given the very cold winter.  However, while my running has backslid over the past three months (I’m no longer as good of a runner as I once was), I have increased my lifts – Squat +25lbs (190 to 215lbs), Benchpress +25lbs (85 to 110lbs), Deadlift +50lbs (215 to 265lbs), and Overhead Press +15lbs (70 to 85lbs).  (I did not increase on my Rows, but that’s because my range of motion in my initial row form was wrong, leading me to have larger weights than merited.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the eating front, things have also become less consistent.  I have been able to mostly keep up a healthy diet, though I have had a lot of struggles with eating junk food that I need to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I’m telling myself to keep up the good work.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/personal-review-for-december-2013-february-2014/&quot;&gt;Personal Review for December 2013 - February 2014&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on March 26, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Interview with Ryan Carey]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/interview-with-ryan-carey/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/interview-with-ryan-carey</id>
  <published>2014-03-24T14:42:19Z</published>
  <updated>2014-03-24T14:42:19Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some people have committed a great deal of their lives to trying to best make the world a better place. I’m trying to sit down with some of these people and learn more about their thoughts and motivations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I sit down with Ryan Carey, who has spent a lot of time working on various projects to make the world a better place, from setting up the utilitarian forum, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.felicifia.org/&quot;&gt;Felicifia&lt;/a&gt;, to co-creating an “effective altruist” meetup group in Melbourne, Australia.  He is now currently collaborating with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.leverageresearch.org/&quot;&gt;Leverage Research&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://centreforeffectivealtruism.org/&quot;&gt;Centre for Effective Altruism&lt;/a&gt; on research into the far future and associated risks.  Ryan has recently been blogging about his thoughts and experiences on &lt;a href=&quot;http://careyryan.com/&quot;&gt;his personal blog&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/interview-with-ryan-carey/profile.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hi Ryan, good to talk to you. Let’s start off with your origin story. How did you first get interested in effective altruism?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; Ah, I learnt about effective altruism through the idea of utilitarianism. I had been reading philosophers like Daniel Dennett, and neuroscientists like VS Ramachandran.  I wanted to know about big questions relating to consciousness and ethics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in high-school, and I had mentioned to my mother some of the things that I had been reading, and it came to her mind that there was an old professor who had once taught her some lessons in bioethics and she had a book for me by that author… That book was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Practical-Ethics-Peter-Singer/dp/0521707684&quot;&gt;Practical Ethics&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Singer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I read his ideas about animals, poverty, and ethics in general, it just clicked for me - he seemed so reasonable and rational.  I went on to learn about this philosophy and gather others who shared that interest online. Many years later when the effective altruist and rationality movements developed, that just crystallized my thinking about how to make the world better and drove me to take more concrete actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Cool!  I was influenced from utilitarianism to effective altruism myself.  But I know a lot of other utilitarians who aren’t effective altruists and just are content to speculate and philosophize without doing anything.  It frustrates me.  What do you think compelled you made this jump to action?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; If only I knew – then we could just swing by all of the utilitarians and activate them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I know is that knowing that suffering is bad, or that you would like people’s experienced to be improved, is very far from feeling empowered to do something about it.  I’d speculate that there are personality factors involved - some people are naturally conscientious. A cynic might say naturally compelled by guilt, although that’s not my experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, every time I’ve been involved with other people who are motivated, then I become socially engaged with that group, and it drives me to do more things that I think that they will find exciting and impressive. So I’ve passed through &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.felicifia.org&quot;&gt;Felicifia&lt;/a&gt;, my utilitarian forum, and then into &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lesswrong.com&quot;&gt;LessWrong&lt;/a&gt;, and through the effective altruist community as well, and at every step I’ve found a lot of people who I like and enjoy being around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That would certainly be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.overcomingbias.com/&quot;&gt;the Hansonian explanation&lt;/a&gt; - that charity is not about doing good, it’s about getting social points. And I guess my experience is pretty consistent with the idea that social points have played a factor at driving me to do more every step of the way.  But I’ve just been lucky in that the people I surround myself with and respect tend to care very much about productivity. So I get social points by starting projects that have a large expected impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I guess Robin would agree that we can signal an expectation of effectiveness from others - I’ve mostly been activated by enjoying the company of other EAs - social signalling used for good, and I think there should be more of it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;A brutally honest and self-aware answer, as much as I’d like to hope there’s more to EA than runaway signalling!  Even so, do you think there’s a way we could harness this desire for social points to get more people to want to do good?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, well I think it already happens, and it’s really good. I think that effective altruist groups are popping up all over the world.  Some of them are branded by EA in general, like my new group in Melbourne, but most of them are broadly under the umbrellas of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.givingwhatwecan.org&quot;&gt;Giving What We Can&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.80000hours.org&quot;&gt;80,000 Hours&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these groups deliver a lot of value to attendees, people learn a lot of fascinating ideas and get to build really close social relationships.  But at the same time, these groups challenge people to integrate a lot of challenging ideas into their behaviour, like the idea of earning to give and the idea that researching the future is important and neglected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think of LessWrong as an effective altruist group too. It’s nominally a group for rationality, but almost everyone is altruistic when you get down far enough. LessWrong shares EAs’ affinity for the scientific method and for evaluating consequences.  In turn, EAs frequently share LW-esque views about biases and epistemology.  They’re sister groups in Melbourne, and I think everywhere, so I think all of these communities are tremendously important for encouraging people to do good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;It’s certainly cool that you’ve got to be a part of the effective altruism wave with &lt;a href=&quot;http://careyryan.com/end-of-year-review-of-effective-altruism-melbourne/&quot;&gt;EA Melbourne&lt;/a&gt;.  But that’s a pretty big initiative.  How did EA Melbourne get it’s start?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; It started when we were contacted by Giving What We Can Central.  I was notified that Rangi de Silva was in Melbourne - another doctor in training who was interested in starting a group there.  So I contacted absolutely everyone I could think of - the central coordinators of Giving What We Can, 80,000 Hours, THINK, Leverage Research, everyone I knew from the Monash University’s philosophy society, and from the local LessWrong group, as well as some old friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few of us met in a coffee shop to decide what we wanted to do and the very first social event was well attended right away, which was excellent.  I’m glad to see that they’ve continued to go from strength to strength after I’ve left and my co-collaborator Brayden stepped down, by hosting CFAR, who spoke to an audience of 70.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes regular, reliable timely work to coordinate things and a network who will attend, I think those are the main things.  That’s what I would suggest to someone trying to launch an EA group, and it’s glad to see that EA Melbourne certainly still has those going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Do you think anything else made EA Melbourne a success, or was it just sheer hard work?  What would be some tips you might give to people who want to organize EA groups in their own local communities?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; I think that the amount of work required is pretty patchy. You can’t just disappear from the planet and spend two months without organizing anything. In particular, you need to be present to arrange things on a weekly basis at the start.  But it’s mostly just basic logistics like setting a venue, a topic, and maybe a speaker, and inviting people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You just need to make sure that you give people a reason to come, they need to know somebody who will be there, and the group need to be nice people - as of course most EAs are - and they need to have something interesting to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start a group, I recommend contacting the central EA groups to get them to introduce you to anyone interested who lives locally and gathering a few people who are willing to throw their social networks into the project.  The Central EA groups can offer a little support remotely, but mostly having a kind, sociable and gender-balanced seed-group seems to often lead to a virtuous cycle that grows itself.  It just takes strong existing social networks and a couple of months of good events to bootstrap that.  I’ve elaborated on these tips in &lt;a href=&quot;http://careyryan.com/ten-simple-tricks-to-meet-effective-altruists-and-you-wont-believe-what-happened-next/&quot;&gt;an article on my blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;That’s great advice.  Thanks!  But you’ve moved on from EA Melbourne.  What lead you to give all that up?  What are you doing now?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; The thing with EA groups is that people always ask you questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the purpose of this group&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can I volunteer for you or others?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who should I donate to?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the most important work to do, apart from recruitment. i.e. we can build social networks for so long, but what should we do afterwards?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These questions are interesting, important and complex. So I set out to develop better answers to these questions. I feel that the answers lie in the area of improving the far future. However, it’s very unclear what we can do to best prepare society to flourish in even 10 or 100 years from now and so I decided that I had to find out an answer to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My best plan for doing this was to travel to the hubs of EA and rationality to get up to speed on others’ progress. I’ve begun 2013 by being in San Francisco where I have collaborated with The Center for Applied Rationality and Leverage Research and I will do a similar thing in Oxford later this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the way the goal is to learn how to produce a better future, including a major subquestion: what kind of people we need to do that work? I am currently doing some research on some of those questions while also trying to build a movement of people to help. I’ll probably be split evenly between research and movement-building over the coming six months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically, EA Melbourne was a valuable project but now I’m running out of new ideas to share with them and I think I need to meet experts who have thought about things for longer in greater detail to keep learning. Also during the time when I was doing EA Melbourne I was working as a doctor there and now that I have finished my internship year I have the option to take on other responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;What made you think that producing a better future is more important than, say, working on global poverty or nonhuman animal rights?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; The best version that I have heard of the argument is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GctnYAYcMhI&quot;&gt;a lecture by Max Tegmark at an old Singularity Summit&lt;/a&gt;. His idea is that future is so vast, in terms of time and space, and yet its value comes from the fact that we are here to see it. Now we can determine whether our civilization will grow across the universe or conversely whether nothing interesting happens again anywhere ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I value the lives of people in a civilization a million years from now the same as lives of people now, so it seems so much worse if we muck things up cosmically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it’s grandiose to want to save the world, it is egotistical to think that everything important is going to happen in one time and space, when we live in a universe that is so much larger - to think that our current experiences are the best that the universe has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How exactly to secure our future, and ensure that everyone has better lives, including non-human animals is a very complex question, but i think that it is also the most important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;What do you think of the current work being done on this topic?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; I think that &lt;a href=&quot;http://yudkowsky.net/&quot;&gt;Eliezer Yudkowsky&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nickbostrom.com/&quot;&gt;Nick Bostrom&lt;/a&gt; have done the most in performing and popularizing this research.  I think they have robust arguments that artificial intelligence poses the largest extinction risk over the next century. Consider that one by one, computers have basically taken on tasks that are more impressive and complicated like chess, go, jeopardy and now driving.  The extent to which we are using computers, the diversity of jobs for which we turn to them in our day to day lives has greatly increased over the last decade. Our computers are networked much more closely and we spend much more time with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If computers continue to get more intelligent in slightly more abstract ways year upon year for another few decades, the world will already look very strange to humans today.  If these systems take on ever more of the properties of autonomy and goal-directedness of high-frequency trading systems and military robots, then we can envisage machines overtaking the intelligence of humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you reached such a situation, it very quickly becomes important that the robots are embedded with some kind of ethics or human values and I think the folks at MIRI have good arguments that we can expect computing to be increasingly goal-directed, that this could happen quickly, and that it would take some extreme kind of precision to create a machine intelligence with values that create a happy outcome for humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence is one issue that plays a big part in many people’s models of the future, and I think it’s an important one.  However it’s only one issue.  There are a range of other global catastrophic risks including asteroids, supervolcanoes, bioterrorism, and nuclear war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holden has recently argued that we should consider our developmental trajectory as a civilisation to be anomalous by historical standards and that any of a number of global catastrophic risks could cause civilisation to take humanity off its favourable developmental trajectory.  I agree with him that research on Global Catastrophic Risks in general is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also advocates that a bunch of strategies like alleviating poverty can have positive flow-through effects that will set our civilisation on a better long-run trajectory and I think that there are lots of conceivable interventions that Nick Beckstead would describe as broad-based including improving collaboration and rationality, that could conceivably make things go a lot better in the long run.  We could also enhance human intelligence or human morality.  There are almost endless possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage, I find the narrower research on global catastrophic risks and artificial intelligence has the most compelling case for improving the far future, but I’m not sure if I have good reasons for that and I think that the field could easily be broken wide-open by an academic is informed and able to think more clearly about these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Do you think you could be that kind of informed academic who breaks the field open?  If not, what do you expect to do?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; I doubt I can outdo all of Eliezer, Paul Christiano, Carl Shulman and all of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fhi.ox.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;FHI&lt;/a&gt;.  But I hope that I can understand the field enough to know what kind of people are required, what kind of infrastructure can be provided to support their work, to publicise it and to reach out to gifted young people who might be interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Do you have specific plans of action yet?  Or are you still thinking?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; Both! And I think I always plan to be!  Actually, mostly the second one, because my plans mostly involve gathering more people together to help me think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MY two projects are &lt;a href=&quot;https://impact.hackpad.com/EA-Blog-Compilation-Introduction-B87PSZopY4f&quot;&gt;an EA Handbook&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://impact.hackpad.com/Effective-Altruist-Community-Blog-using-LW-Codebase-lGglK2kN3Ll&quot;&gt;an Online Community called The Most Good&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EA Handbook is a document that will introduce people to effective altruism and bring them up to speed on these questions. I’m preparing this with Will MacAskill. So far, we have collected many existing essays and a few authors have agreed to write some more to describe how everybody can contribute to existing organisations. This project should be finished by the middle of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The online community The Most Good will provide a central location for EA blog posts, discussion and meetups.  To avoid duplicating work, we’re using &lt;a href=&quot;http://trikeapps.com/&quot;&gt;Trike Apps&lt;/a&gt;, who will build the software using the LessWrong codebase. This website is currently in the design stage, but hopefully it will be completed by mid-year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; _If you don’t mind me asking, why are you doing all this yourself?  Earlier you said you were training to be a doctor.  I’ll bet on a doctor’s salary you could “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.effective-altruism.com/what-earning-give-0/&quot;&gt;earn to give&lt;/a&gt;” and hire multiple people to work on these projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; I might end up going back to being a doctor, but there are three reasons that I’m not doing that right now: (1) I don’t know who to fund, (2) I think that many of these future-oriented projects are more time than money constrained, and (3) my uncertainties around my skill and fit are greater for research and activism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On (1), in global poverty reduction, we think that charities vary in up to 100x effectiveness.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cser.org/&quot;&gt;Center for the Study of Existential Risk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.intelligence.org&quot;&gt;Machine Intelligence Research Institute&lt;/a&gt;, FHI, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gcrinstitute.org/&quot;&gt;Global Catostrophic Risk Institute&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.centreforeffectivealtruism.org&quot;&gt;Centre for Effective Altruism&lt;/a&gt; are all working on issues relating to the far future, and I currently have very little idea which is the most effective. In research in particular, we know that some like &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Norman_Borlaug&quot;&gt;Norman Borlaug&lt;/a&gt; can be enormously effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, in terms of citations, we know that &lt;a href=&quot;http://80000hours.org/blog/65-should-you-go-into-research-part-1&quot;&gt;some researchers outperform others by many orders of magnitude&lt;/a&gt;. In future-oriented research in particular, this seems to remain the case. Some futurists clearly have very poor intellectual methodologies and so I expect that in future-oriented research, I think this should remain the case. Moreover, there are no good metrics for the impact of future-oriented research. Nick Bostrom and Eliezer Yudkowsky are not merely aiming for publications and citations, and neither should they be. So these can only be a small part of my assessment. I can ask experts that I respect whose research they value the most, and I think that this is an important part of the solution, but it is also somewhat circular. It is hard to decide who to respect without any technical understanding, and this can be biased by halo effects that come from their attractiveness, demeanor or social competence. So I think at this stage, I need greater technical understanding in order to decide who to give to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On (2), I think that many of these future-oriented projects are more time than money constrained. I know less than a hundred people who are interested and able to perform research into the far future and build a surrounding movement. By contrast, I know several people who have demonstrated their willingness to support ambitious research agendas, such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Thiel&quot;&gt;Peter Thiel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jaan_Tallinn&quot;&gt;Jaan Tallin&lt;/a&gt;, Matt Wage and Matt Fallshaw. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One has to ask what we know that Peter Thiel doesn’t that is preventing him from giving all his funding to the MIRI or Jaan to the CSER. I think they know that their ability to turn cash into recruiting and employing valuable researchers is limited, or at least the marginal returns will decline at some point. Another line of reasoning is that many people are currently pursuing earn-to-give careers in finance and entrepreneurship that will take 3-10 years to pay off, and so it should soon become easier to get effective projects funded. Also most thought-leaders and organization-leaders who I have talked to consider that their organizations are more constrained by talent that funding. Of course, these statements are misleading or false if taken as absolutes. They make sense only when one talks about how much funding weighed against how much talent or recruitment ability. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On (3), given this information about the wide range of usefulness of far-future oriented research, I am highly uncertain about my impact there. I am also pretty uncertain about my value as an entrepreneur, but less so. Medicine is by far the most reliable option. Currently, it seems best to narrow my uncertainty on my impact as a researcher or in performing recruitment and movement-building. Then, I might move on to start-ups. If all this falls through, then I’ll happily be a doctor and pool my funding with the rest. Although even then it seems good to live in or visit the EA hubs to stay motivated and inform my donations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;How were you able to quickly integrate yourself with the San Francisco and Oxford EA communities in order to get involved?  What could an aspiring EA do to follow in your footsteps and also work on making a better future?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; Professionally, I think EAs and rationalists can easily see your value if you are conscientious or have achieved some broad competencies. I recommend asking to be introduced to some of the leaders of these organizations by your best connected EA friends or cold-emailing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Socially, I think EAs and wonderful and inclusive people. If you have some social skills, or even if you don’t have many social skills, but you have interesting ideas, people will tend to like you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My advice regarding integrating into the San Francisco and Oxford communities would be - just do it - I think that travelling to Oxford and San Francisco’s Bay Area are key steps in my intellectual development. Interning at the Center for Applied Rationality or the Center for Effective Altruism are good steps.  Or, one can attend a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rationality.org/&quot;&gt;CFAR workshop&lt;/a&gt; or get career counselling from 80,000 Hours.  And I am always happy to be contacted to answer questions and help with introductions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;What is a typical day for you like these days?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; Every day I read about topics that I think might improve my strategic understanding.  I try to research techniques recommended by people I respect. Recently I’ve been researching intelligence - I take creatine every day and measure its effect with a 20 minute battery of cognitive tests.  For the last fortnight I have been practising speed-reading, because I think that it is important to front-load the acquisition of skills that will help further productivity and research. I am doing emails to prepare the handbook. I discuss with researchers at Leverage and the Center for Applied Rationality regarding to how we can be smarter, more emotionally stable, and less biased. When I learn something new or useful, I write it down on my blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these professional jobs, I’m most confident in the importance of speed-reading, movement-building, and researching creatine. My ongoing plan is contingent on what works and I expect I’ll answer very differently two months from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of EA, I like to see blues, funk and soul music, and comedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;What do you think is the most important thing you’re not doing?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; Probably what &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jason_Gaverick_Matheny&quot;&gt;Gaverick Matheny&lt;/a&gt; is doing.  He is the project manager at IARPA responsible for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iarpa.gov/Programs/ia/ACE/ace.html&quot;&gt;the Aggregative Contingent Estimation program&lt;/a&gt; in which the good judgement project are competing and aggregating opinions to improve probabilistic forecasts of real events. I think that improving collective prediction and collective decision-making is important for stability and cooperation between governments and that it’s important to improve the sanity level of populations and large govenrments, and this work seems like a step in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Well, I think I’m out of questions.  It was great getting a chance to talk with you and learn more about you.  Do you have anything else you want to pass on to EAs before we leave?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RC:&lt;/strong&gt; I would say congrats on being one of the special few who is keen to change the world. By meeting others in your hometown and in EA hubs, you can learn faster and become more productive. Try to learn about the questions that expert EAs are asking themselves, and think about how you might fit in. EA is in a fascinating sociological and intellectual position, and I hope there are great things to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thanks for the interview Peter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PH:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Anytime.  It was great to hear more about you and I look forward to talking with you again sometime!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/interview-with-ryan-carey/&quot;&gt;Interview with Ryan Carey&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on March 24, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Behold!  The New Site!]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/behold-the-new-site/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/behold-the-new-site</id>
  <published>2014-03-14T14:39:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-03-14T14:39:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think it’s important to keep things fresh.  It seems like at least once a year or so, I change what the site looks like.  This year, server problems, financial costs, and other bloat inspired me to move away from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wordpress.org&quot;&gt;Wordpress&lt;/a&gt; and paid hosting on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dreamhost.com&quot;&gt;Dreamhost&lt;/a&gt; to the wonderful land of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll static blog&lt;/a&gt; hosted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt;.  Back five years ago when I first signed on with Dreamhost, none of these tools existed.  Now, it’s time that I finally adopt them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll still have to get used to writing in Markdown.  But hopefully you find this site faster and easier to use than before.  It sure looks better on mobile phones.  Let me know if you have any comments.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/behold-the-new-site/&quot;&gt;Behold!  The New Site!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on March 14, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sunday Links #24]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-24/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-24</id>
  <published>2014-03-10T01:28:59Z</published>
  <updated>2014-03-10T01:28:59Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I still do these…  Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://slatestarcodex.com/2013/06/14/the-virtue-of-silence/&quot;&gt;“The Virtue of Silence”&lt;/a&gt;: “Leah Libresco writes a couple of essays on an ethical dilemma reported in the New York Times. In the course of a confidential medical history, a doctor hears her patient is suffering from stress-related complaints after having sent an innocent man to prison. The doctor wants to know whether it is ethical to report the matter to the police. The Times’ columnist says yes – it would save the poor prisoner. Leah says no – violating medical confidentiality creates an expectation that medical confidentiality will be violated in the future, thus dooming patients who are too afraid to talk about drug use or gay sex or other potentially embarrassing but important medical risk factors.  But both sides are ignoring the much bigger dilemma lurking one meta-level up: is it ethical to debate this dilemma in the New York Times?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://utilitarian-essays.com/robustness-against-uncertainty.html&quot;&gt;Charity Cost-Effectiveness in an Uncertain World&lt;/a&gt;: “Evaluating the effectiveness of our actions, or even just whether they’re positive or negative by our values, is very difficult. One approach is to focus on clear, quantifiable metrics and assume that the larger, indirect considerations just kind of work out. Another way to deal with uncertainty is to focus on actions that seem likely to have generally positive effects across many scenarios, and often this approach amounts to meta-level activities like encouraging positive-sum institutions, philosophical inquiry, and effective altruism in general. When we consider flow-through effects of our actions, the seemingly vast gaps in cost-effectiveness among charities are humbled to more modest differences, and we begin to find more worth in the diversity of activities that different people are pursuing. Those who have abnormal values may be more wary of a general “promote wisdom” approach to shaping the future, but it seems plausible that all value systems will ultimately benefit in expectation from a more cooperative and reflective future populace.”
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/whynojobs&quot;&gt;“The Reason So Many People are Unemployed”&lt;/a&gt;: “A good way to wrap your head around this is to think about a much smaller case: instead of the whole economy, let’s think about a now-famous babysitting co-op on Capitol Hill. Instead of dollars, the co-op used its own scrip that was worth an hour of babysitting time. When you wanted to go out, you’d pay a couple hours to someone else to watch your kids; then when they wanted to go out, they’d pay you or someone else to do the same for them.  It all worked great for a while, until one day they found they had too few pieces of scrip. Every couple had only a couple hours left and, having so little, they didn’t want to waste it. So they all decided to save it for a very special occasion. This was kind of an incredible situation — even though there were people who wanted someone to babysit their kids, and people who were willing to do just that, the deal didn’t happen, simply because the co-op hadn’t printed enough colored pieces of paper. Eventually the co-op learned their mistake, printed some more scrip and handed it out, and everybody went back to babysitting like before and were much happier for it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spring.org.uk/2013/02/the-single-most-effective-method-for-influencing-people-fast.php&quot;&gt;The Single Most Effective Method for Influencing People Fast&lt;/a&gt;: “Influence techniques vary considerably in how effective, ethical and easy to perform they are. At the easy, more ethical end of the spectrum, is affirming someone’s right to choose. This is a benign strategy which happens to have the handy side-effect of increasing persuasion.  But what if you are looking to use a little more effort to get a lot more persuasion-power? Then perhaps the disrupt-then-reframe (DTR) technique is for you.  A word of warning, though: the DTR technique is more of a cheap (but very effective) trick which some might find morally questionable. OK, with the health warning over, here’s what they did in the original study which kicked off this whole line of research.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2013/02/cognitive-democracy-condorcet-with-competence.html&quot;&gt;Cognitive Democracy: Condorcet with Competence&lt;/a&gt;: “We usually think of democracy as a way of aggregating diverse preferences but we can also imagine that we share similar preferences and that what we disagree about is the best way to achieve those preferences. From this perspective, democracy can be thought of as a tool for information aggregation. Using simple probability theory, Condorcet showed in 1785 that even when each individual voter has only a slightly better than chance probability of choosing the bettier of two options the probability that majority rule chooses the better outcome quickly goes to 1 as the number of voters increases (the wisdom of the crowds).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lesswrong.com/r/discussion/lw/iro/systematic_lucky_breaks/&quot;&gt;Systematic Lucky Breaks:&lt;/a&gt; “Many people can point to significant events that improved their lives in a positive way. They often refer to these as ‘lucky breaks’, and take it for granted that such events are rare. But most of the time ‘lucky breaks’ don’t need to be uncommon-you can often reverse engineer the reasons behind them and cause them to happen more frequently. So when a one-off event ends up contributing a lot of value, you should systematically make it part of your life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2013/06/do-unpaid-internships-lead-to-jobs-not-for-college-students/276959/&quot;&gt;“Do Unpaid Internships Lead to Jobs? Not for College Students”&lt;/a&gt;: “The common defense of the unpaid internship is that, even if the role doesn’t exactly pay, it will pay off eventually in the form of a job. Turns out, the data suggests that defense is wrong, at least when it comes to college students.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amid all the focus on how much it costs precisely to save a life, here’s a good reminder from GiveWell that &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.givewell.org/2013/06/11/the-moral-case-for-giving-doesnt-rely-on-questionable-quantitative-estimates/&quot;&gt;the moral case for giving doesn’t rely on questionable quantitative estimates”&lt;/a&gt;: “To us, the strongest form of the challenge is not ‘How much should I give when $X saves a life?’ but ‘How much should I give, knowing that I have massive wealth compared to the global poor?’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://oliveremberton.com/2014/life-is-a-game-this-is-your-strategy-guide/&quot;&gt;Life is a game, this is your strategy guide&lt;/a&gt;.  Cute.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/sunday-links-24/&quot;&gt;Sunday Links #24&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on March 10, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Effective Altruism is Not a Competition]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/effective-altruism-is-not-a-competition/" />
  <id>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/effective-altruism-is-not-a-competition</id>
  <published>2014-03-01T15:08:00Z</published>
  <updated>2014-03-01T15:08:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.everydayutilitarian.com</uri>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the past, some people have suggested that we “gamify” effective altruism some more, and create points for doing altruistic-y things, like donating our money or volunteering our time.  I think this could be a good idea, but rather than seeing individual scores, I’d much rather see a collective team score for EA.  We’d compete as a group to beat our past group selves (make March better than February, for example) rather than compete amongst ourselves as individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several problems with the individual competition model, but the biggest problem is the most fundamental – &lt;strong&gt;effective altruism is not&lt;/strong&gt; (and shouldn’t be) &lt;strong&gt;a competition.&lt;/strong&gt;  Rather, we are a team.  A community.  We all have one common goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know some effective altruists who see EAs like Holden Karnofsky or what not do incredible things, and feel a little bit of resentment at themselves and others; feeling inadequate that they can’t make such a large difference.  This is an important feeling for generating a desire to improve, and keeping a &lt;a href=&quot;http://michaelgr.com/2007/04/15/fixed-mindset-vs-growth-mindset-which-one-are-you/&quot;&gt;growth mindset&lt;/a&gt; in the face of this could lead to great things for you.  However, it’s even more important not to let this get you into depression, &lt;strong&gt;simply because Holden’s success is also your success.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All effective altruists care about is making sure that the world is a better place.  It doesn’t matter who is doing the better-ing.  If Holden, Bill Gates, and Dustin Moskovitz each have 1 billion EA points and you only have five, you should be celebrating the fact that the EA community is collectively at 3 billion and five EA points and that you’re helping.  You shouldn’t feel bad that you’re not doing as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have different skills and abilities.  Growth mindset does say that we each have an ability to be incredibly effective and altruistic, but we still all start with different places.  It’s simply not the case that all of us, right this year, could be making seven figure donations to GiveWell or be putting in 80 hours a week at a top non-profit.  But we all can do our best and try a little harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start seeing ourselves more as a community where everyone has something to offer and celebrate our collective success, not despair over who is or is not the most effective.  Effective altruism shouldn’t be a competition (at least, among individuals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Idea adapted from Brian Tomasik’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://felicifia.org/viewtopic.php?f=10&amp;amp;t=797&quot;&gt;“Teamwork over Envy”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com/essays/effective-altruism-is-not-a-competition/&quot;&gt;Effective Altruism is Not a Competition&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by  at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.everydayutilitarian.com&quot;&gt;Everyday Utilitarian&lt;/a&gt; on March 01, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>